<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A guide to the true religion, or, A discourse directing to make a wise choice of that religion men venture their salvation upon seasonable for these times wherein there are such diversities of opinions and wayes of religion : to inform the ignorant, to resolve the wavering, and to confirm the weak / by I.C., M.A. of T.C.C.</title>
            <author>I. C., M.A. of T.C.C.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1669</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 146 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 56 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A34207</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C57</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R5667</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13688915</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13688915</idno>
            <idno type="VID">101381</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A34207)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 101381)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 840:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A guide to the true religion, or, A discourse directing to make a wise choice of that religion men venture their salvation upon seasonable for these times wherein there are such diversities of opinions and wayes of religion : to inform the ignorant, to resolve the wavering, and to confirm the weak / by I.C., M.A. of T.C.C.</title>
                  <author>I. C., M.A. of T.C.C.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 103 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Andrew Anderson and are to be sold at his house ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1669.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Conversion --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Salvation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:101381:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:101381:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A GUIDE TO THE True Religion: OR A DISCOURSE Directing to make a wiſe <hi>CHOICE</hi> of that Religion Men venture their Salvation upon: Seaſonable for theſe Times, wherein there are ſuch Diverſities of Opinions and wayes of Religion.</p>
            <p>To inform the Ignorant, to reſolve the Wavering, and to confirm the Weak.</p>
            <p>By <hi>I. C. M. A.</hi> of <hi>T. C. C.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Joſh. 24.15.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>And if it ſeem evil unto you to ſerve the Lord; Chuſe you this day whom you will ſerve, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Gods — But as for me, and my Houſe, we will ſerve the Lord.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>EDINB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RGH,</hi> Printed by <hi>Andrew Anderſon,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Houſe, on the North ſide of the Croſs, <hi>Anno</hi> 1669.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:101381:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:101381:2"/>
            <head>A Premonition to the Reader, ſhewing the occaſion and intendment of the <hi>Diſcourſe.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THere is no good Chriſtian, but is ready upon all juſt occaſions to expreſs his ſad reſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the wofull Diviſions and dangerous Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, wherewith the Churches of Chriſt in theſe Kingdoms have been for many years paſt, and ſtill are ſo diſtracted; for notwithſtanding that our civill Wars are through the mercy of God en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>did, yet our Religious jars and rents are not heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Indeed, how can any pious Soul conſider the great diſhonour done thereby to the Holy Name of God, the reproach to the Chriſtian Religion, the great ſcandal to thoſe ſometimes famous Churches (which are now, hereby become infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous through the World) yea, the apparent ruine threatned by theſe things, and not break out into ſad lamentation for the ſame! Surely this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> a Lamentaion, and ſhall be for a Lamentation.</p>
            <p>And although the ſerious conſideration of thoſe evils, in order to the repairing and healing of them, and the preventing the publick ruine threatned to the Church and State thereby, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth to the wiſedome and zeal of thoſe that be in place of eminency, and are veſted with power and authority requiſite thereunto; yet Private Chriſtians in a lower ſtation and capacity, cannot but have their eyes upon the ſad influence thoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ings have upon their deareſt Friends and
<pb facs="tcp:101381:3"/>Neighbours with whom they converſe, and in their behalf meditate upon ſome remedy for the ſame. Certain it is, that the malignant influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence theſe things have on the common ſort is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſad; whilſt gazing on thoſe ſad conteſting mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Religion, Some continue meer <hi>Scepticks,</hi> ever wavering, and not knowing what way of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion to chuſe, and ſo neglect to be of any; Some are profeſſed Atheiſts, or profane Wretches; Others be ſeduced into dangerous Errors as <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery, Socinianiſm, Quakeriſm,</hi> &amp;c. Many ingage in contentions they know not why, nor for what: And the greateſt part of Chriſtians wofully ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled in their Profeſſion.</p>
            <p>The intendment of theſe Papers, is to propoſe ſome help againſt thoſe evils, and to guide and direct thoſe that are apt to miſcarry through oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of the diverſities of Opinions and wayes found a mongſt us. Wherein they are firſt excited to make a wiſe Choice of that Religion they ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture their Eternal Salvation upon, and are infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med how to do it. Indeavours are uſed to fix and eſtabliſh them in the truth of the Christian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and to acquaint them with the great and Fundamental Doctrines and Duties threrof ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary unto Salvation, which have been owned by all Chriſtians and Churches in all places and ages; and to perſwade to believe and obey them, as that whereupon their eternal ſafety depends. Then our diſcourſe deſcends to points of a ſecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dary and inferior Nature that are controverted
<pb facs="tcp:101381:3"/>amongſt wiſe and godly Chriſtians, and directions are laid down how to find out the right and ſafe way for Faith and practice in ſuch things (eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially when we are neceſſitated to hold forth a profeſſion of our ſelves therein) Wherewith is ſhewed alſo what tenderneſſe and reſpect, is to be uſed toward thoſe that differ from us in thoſe things, whilſt, in the mean time, we carry it at a greater diſtance with thoſe that err fundemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally, and ſubvert the Chriſtian Faith, and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. All which counſels being evidenced to be good and wholſome, will manifeſtly declare, Thoſe to be the moſt approved and judicious Chriſtians, who (under all thoſe great changes and revolutions which have been amongſt us of latter times) have eſpecially exerciſed their zeal for the maintaining of the Fundament all Doctrines of the Goſpel, and the practice and power of Godlineſſe; as alſo for the preſerving the peace of the Church, and love and union amongſt Chriſtians: whilſt in the mean time they have ſhewed greateſt moderation and condeſcenſion, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards thoſe that differ in controverted Points of a lower Nature, even to a degree of complyance alſo with the ſtream of the times in ſome things, which ſeem in themſelves leſs deſireable and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convenient (provided in their Conſciences they judge them not to be ſinful) if conducing to the furtherance of the Goſpel, the peace of the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and Salvation of Souls.</p>
            <p>Indeed this will be judged by ſome raſh and
<pb facs="tcp:101381:4"/>cenſorious Spirits to be Hypocriſie, Time-ſerving, er ſelf-ſeeking, and ſuch perſons may be bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for Temporizers, Turn-coats or Apoſtates, or what not; but when things ſhall be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered in calmneſs and Sobriety, Such will be found the greateſt friends of Chriſt and the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion: and ſuch actions moſt conſonant to Scripture commands, and to the examples of the Saints recorded therein; whereas ſuch as are found departing from any Fundamental and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally confeſſed points of faith or Practice, Theſe imputations may be more warrantably charged upon them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reader,</hi> Let theſe ſad and wofull differences, errours, and debates, provoke thee to examine the grounds thy profeſſion is built upon; to ſtudy more the verity and excellency of the Chriſtian Religion, and be better eſtabliſhed therein; to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, believe, love, and obey the great and neceſſary Principles thereof; humbly to ſeek of God the diſcovery of his mind in things more dark and controverted; and to exerciſe more Chriſtian love and charity thoſe that are not of the ſame perſwaſion or practice with thee therein: And then, thou wilt be ſecured from the danger of thoſe evils; yea, they will prove advantagious to thy greateſt good, although intended by Satan for thy hurt. <hi>To help</hi> thee herein, is the intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and deſigne of this diſcourſe, in order where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, the bleſſing of the Lord is humbly implo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to go along with the ſame.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:101381:4"/>
            <head>THE CONTENTS. OF The ſeverall CHAPTERS.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. 1.</hi> REligion the grand concernment of Man in this World Great differences about it. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of a wiſe and deliberate chuſing ones Religion. A propoſition laid down, which is the Subject matter of the following Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe. <hi>Page 1.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. 2.</hi> Shewing, wherein this wiſe Chuſing ones Religion ſtands, and what Acts concurr thereunto. <hi>Page 5.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. 3.</hi> Conſiderations evidencing it a princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal Point of wiſdome for a Man to make a right Choice of that Religion he profeſſes in the World, and ventures his Eternal Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion upon. <hi>Page 13</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. 4.</hi> Wherein the Practice of this Duty is inſiſted upon, and Directions given, how to chuſe the true Religion amongſt ſo many as are in the World. All other Religions being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected, The Chriſtian Religion is evidenced to be the only true Religion. <hi>Page 23.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. 5.</hi> Further directions how to chuſe the right and ſafe way amongſt ſuch diverſities of Sects and Opinions as be amongſt Chriſtians. A Diſcovery of the Fundamental Doctrines
<pb facs="tcp:101381:5"/>of Faith and practical duties of Godlineſs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally embraced by all Chriſtians in all times and places, with advice in reference unto them. <hi>Page 30</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. 6.</hi> Other directions in Points of a Secun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dary Nature, that are not ſo clearly laid down in Scripture, nor unanimouſly received by all Christians, but are Problemaical; and yet there is a neceſſity to be of the one or other Perſwaſion, how to make a right choiſe in ſuch a Caſe. 4. Rules about this. <hi>Page 41</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. 7.</hi> A cloſer application of the foregoing diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to the preſent State of the Church in <hi>England,</hi> with particular advice in reference to the different Wayes and Profeſſions found amongſt us. <hi>Pag. 50.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. 8.</hi> Wherein the great controverſie of Communion with, or Separation from the Church of <hi>England,</hi> is diſcuſſed. A view of what is therein Praiſe-worthy; and of what is diſallowable in the Judgement of thoſe that ſcruple Communion with her. Directions ſui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted thereunto. <hi>Page. 81</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP 9.</hi> Wherein are laid down ſome general Rules of Caution to preſerve Chriſtians from raſh and unjuſt Separation. The Concluſion of the Diſcourſe. <hi>Page 89.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:101381:5"/>
               <head>CHAP. 1.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Religion the grand concernment of Man in this World, great differences about the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of a wiſe and deliberate Chuſing ones Religion. The counſel of <hi>Joſhua</hi> to the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> applyed to us. A propoſition laid down, which is the Subject matter of the following Diſcourſe.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>THE buſineſs of Religion is the grand concernment that all of us are ſent into the World to mind, and therefore God hath, in the very fram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of mans nature, laid ſo deep an impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion thereof in us, that there's no Nation ſo barbarous and inhumane, but doth place this amongſt the greateſt matters, that they judge themſelves to be interreſſed in; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch as ſome obſerve, Religion is more proper to man then reaſon. All men, and on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly men have a ſmatch of Religion; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as ſome ſhew of reaſon is found in many Beaſts. <hi>Lactant. de ira Dei, Solus home ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pientia inſtructus eſt, ut Religionem ſolus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligat, &amp; hac eſt hominis atque bruterum vel pracipua vel ſola diſtantia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But as it is a thing all do profeſs them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves intereſſed in; ſo there's nothing in
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:101381:6"/>all the world, men are at greater diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences about; ſome taking up one Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and ſome another, as pleaſes them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves beſt; yea each Nation almoſt have choſen a peculiar Deity, as we find in Scripture, one ſerving <hi>Baal,</hi> another <hi>Dagon</hi> others <hi>Moloch</hi> or <hi>Aſhtaroth, &amp;c</hi> Some wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping the <hi>Sun,</hi> others the <hi>Moon</hi> or <hi>Starrs,</hi> and almoſt every Creature whence they received any benefite: and ſome have not been wanting that have adored the Devil himſelf. How greatly then doth it behove every one to make a wiſe choiſe of that God he intends to ſerve, and of that Religion he means to profeſs in the World and to live and die in? That he may firſt chuſe the true Religion and true God, and then cleave to him with full purpoſe of heart, as <hi>Barnabas</hi> exhorts, <hi>Acts</hi> 11.23. And the rather becauſe of the great impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance thereof; Mans eternall happineſſe or miſery depends on the right knowing and; acknowledging God, and ſerving him; or his miſtake about it: according to the witneſſe of Chriſt himſelf <hi>Iohn</hi> 17.3. <hi>This is life eternall to know</hi> (ſo as to acknowledge unto godlineſs) <hi>Thee the only true God, &amp; Ieſus Christ whom thou haſt ſent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We read in the ſtory of the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> the vanity of mans nature in matters of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion;
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:101381:6"/>though no Nation under the whole Heavens had greater diſcoveries of the true God then they had; both by his Word and Oracles, inſtructing them from Heaven, and giving them his Law on Mount <hi>Sinai,</hi> and teaching them by his Prophets, the infallible interpreters of that Law: as alſo by his mighty works, bringing them out of <hi>Egypt</hi> by his out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtretched Arm, working ſignes and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, dividing the Red-Sea, giving them water out of the Rock and bread and Fleſh from Heaven in a Wilderneſſe, and guid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them by a Cloud of ſmoake, and a Pillar of Fire: yet how apt were they to turn away from God, and to worſhip o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Gods, even of the <hi>Egyptians</hi> and <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naanites,</hi> whom God caſt out before them? A pregnant inſtance whereof we have in the buſineſs of the Golden Calf, though but forty dayes before, they heard the Law proclaimed in the greateſt ſolemnity that ever was, even by the Miniſtry of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels with Thunder, Lightning and Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake, which wrought ſuch plyableneſs in their Spirit, that they profeſſed, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the Lord ſhould ſpeak to them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> That that they would doe <hi>Deut.</hi> 5.27. Yet when <hi>Moſes</hi> was but a while withdrawn from them upon the Mount, they quickly turned
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:101381:7"/>and made them a Calf to worſhip, after the manner of <hi>Egypt.</hi> This being obſerved by <hi>Joſhua</hi> his Succeſſour, he became jealous over them with a godly jealouſie; and being fearfull that when he was gone from them, they ſhould do the like, He indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to eſtabliſh them in the true Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and to bind them to the Lord in the ſtrongeſt bonds, <hi>Joſh.</hi> 24. He bids them, verſe 15. <hi>Chuſe deliberatly what God they would ſerve,</hi> directing them by his own example; and then when they had delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately choſen Jehovah for their God, he binds them unto him by a ſolemn covenant, <hi>verſe</hi> 25. And ſets up a laſting remembrance of it.</p>
               <p>Theſe things are written for our inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and do ſhew what a Spirit there is in us, even an evil heart of unbelief in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parting from the living God, as well as in them formerly (as the Apoſtle ſhews, <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.12.) Though we have as full diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coveries of God as they had, and greater means of knowledge by Goſpel-light, to know God and Jeſus Chriſt: Yet our hearts are equally fickle and ready to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake God, and the true Religion, and (as the Apoſtle taxeth the <hi>Galathians</hi>) to turn to another Goſpel and another Chriſt then we have received, yea to another God, the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:101381:7"/>World, our Luſts, or Satan, to ſerve them more then the true God. Therefore this counſel of <hi>Joſhua</hi> may be as ſeaſonable to us now as to them formerly, <hi>viz. To</hi> chuſe deliberately and ſeriouſly what God we will ſerve; and then to reſolve to cleave unto him for ever: or wiſely to chuſe that Religion, we will profeſſe in the World and venture our ſalvation upon; and then to labour to be eſtabliſhed and fixed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, ſo as by no ſtorms of temptation we be removed.</p>
               <p>The urging of this Counſel upon un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſettled and wavering Souls, being the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendment and deſign of this diſcourſe, ſui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to theſe fluctuating and ſhaking times, It may be contracted into this inſuing pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, which ſhall be more fully dilated on in the following Chapters, <hi>viz:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That it is a great point of wiſedom for a Man to make a right Choice of that Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion he means to take up and profeſſe in the World, that he intends to live and die in, &amp; to venture his eternal Salvation upon.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Shewing wherein this wiſe Chuſing our Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion stands, &amp; what acts concur thereunto.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>HAving laid down the propoſition which is the ground of our <hi>Diſcourſe</hi>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:101381:8"/>in the former chapter, we come now to inquire concerning the nature of that <hi>choice</hi> wherein it ſtands, and what things ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarly muſt concurre to make a wiſe choice of that Religion, we intend to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs in the World.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Election</hi> or chuſing (in a generall ſenſe) is an act of the will, proceeding from the previous knowledge and judgement of the underſtanding, whereby amongſt diverſe wayes or means propounded for the at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment of ſome <hi>End,</hi> it doth reſolve upon ſome one above the reſt, that it will ad here unto, and make uſe of for that purpoſe.</p>
               <p>In particular, <hi>Chuſing</hi> ones <hi>Religion,</hi> is alſo an act of the will ariſing from the previous knowledge and judgement of the underſtanding (diſcerning the nature of the thing) whereby amongſt the many dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent Religions (or wayes of ſerving and pleaſing God, and of attaining unto hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe with him) that are found in the World, a man doth pitch and reſolve up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on one above all the reſt (and with rejecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all others) with full purpoſe to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>here unto it, to live and die in it, and even venture a mans ſalvation and happineſs on it.</p>
               <p>Here are 3 Acts wherein this right chu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing ones Religion doth ſtand, to be explai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in order.</p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:101381:8"/>
               <p n="1">1. An act of the <hi>underſtanding,</hi> judging and diſcerning the nature of the thing that the will chuſeth; and its excellencie above al things that come in competition with it; for to a right choice of the will the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding and judgement muſt proceed it: muſt know the nature of it, and diſcern it; good, or elſe its but a blind choice, not becoming a reaſonable creature, and a man may elſe imbrace evil as well as good. The will when is acts regularly follows the Dictate of the underſtanding; this tells what is good, and then what chuſes, as the Palat judgeth of what it taſts, and then the ſtomach or appetite craves it; ſo muſt the underſtanding go before her, &amp; diſcern the nature, verity and goodneſſe of that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, as alſo the falſneſſe, vanity and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerouſneſſe of other Religions before the will can make a right choice of it. Man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a religious creature, by the common inſtinct of his naturall conſcience, is moved ſtrongly to worſhip and ſerve a Deity (as we ſee in all Nations of the Earth) much more when he is further ſtirred up by a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine inſtinct. Now we ſhould conſider as men (as the prophets phraſe is) and not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ert actions of higheſt importance without underſtanding and reaſon, worſhiping we know not what (as Chriſt taxes the <hi>Sama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritans,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:101381:9"/>John</hi> 4.) but give God a reaſonable ſervice, knowing what God we ſerve, and what Religion we take up; and not taking up the next at hand, at adventure, (as moſt men do) that Religion profeſſed where they live, &amp; commended to them by Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, example, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but underſtanding what we do therein, And therefore men that act according to reaſon, will look in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Religions in the World, and judge which is beſt among them; or rather in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Word and Oracles of God himſelf, for they beſt diſcover what God is, and how he will be worſhipped. Therefore if there be any ſuch thing, as Divine Oracles in the world, wherein God hath revealed his will concerning matters of Faith and worſhip, we ſhould have ſpecial recourſe unto them. Now that the holy Scriptures (commonly called the Bible) are ſuch, that is, <hi>the Oracles of the God of Heaven,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he directs us in the knowledge and worſhip of himſelf, and in the way of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion; This may appear even to thoſe that have not yet taken upon them any profeſſion of Religion by ſuch Infallible demonſtrations, as reaſon cannot contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict, <hi>viz.</hi> From theſe characters imprin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted on them which ſhew them to be of God, from the miracles wrought to confirm
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:101381:9"/>them, from that ſpirit of holineſſe ſeen in ſuch as ſeriouſly believe them, from the accompliſhment of a great part of thoſe things revealed therein, even ſuch things as were utterly inviſible and improbable to created underſtandings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore there ſhould be an exact conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the judgement and underſtanding of a man of that Religion revealed in the Scriptures. He ſhould 1. Take a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular view of the principal Doctrines, the great myſteries of faith and duties of godlineſs taught therein, not taking all in the lump together, but having a diſtinct knowledge of them. He whoſe Religion is in the groſs only, and hath no diſtinct apprehenſions of the particular doctrines of faith and duties of godlineſſe, which that Religion teaches, he hath no Religion at all; for how can theſe Doctrines influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence his heart and life to make him fear, and love God truly, and lead him to the power and practice of godlineſſe, if not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctly known and diſcerned by him? Then 2. Hee muſt diſcern the <hi>verity</hi> and <hi>certainty</hi> of theſe Doctrines, that he may venture his ſoul upon them, knowing him in whom he hath believed; for which and it's exceeding neceſſary to be conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant in thoſe Treatiſes which prove the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:101381:10"/>verity of the Chriſtian Religion, and of the Scriptures (wherein it is ſet down) of which many be extant in our own Language. Without this a man ſhal never hold faſt his Religion, eſpecially in trying times. 3. He ſhould know the <hi>excellency</hi> thereof, that its ſuch a Religion as tends moſt to the magnifying of God, and giving glory unto him, to the advancement of man to true happineſs in the love and favor of his God, and neareſt communion with him, and fulleſt conformity unto him. He ſhould often look upon the ſublimity of the myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, the purity of the precepts, excellency of the rewards, and dreadfulneſs of the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments. And thus the underſtanding preceeding in diſcerning and judging the Religion which is to be choſen, is one Act in this <hi>Election.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Act, After the underſtanding doth thus preſent the true Religion before us in the certainty, glory and excellency of it; Then the next Act is for the <hi>Will</hi> to elect, chuſe, and imbrace it, ſolemnly to eſpouſe this Religion, and ſay, It ſhal be mine; It's that I am reſolved to profeſſe, and to venture my eternal ſalvation upon, what ever inconveniences I may meet with in the profeſſion thereof; what ever diſgraces, reproaches, loſſes, Perſecutions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:101381:10"/>yet this Religion I will be of, and this God I will ſerve. We muſt ſit down and con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſider what it will coſt us to be Chriſtians, and then eſpouſe the Chriſtian Religion, and take it for better, for worſe, embrace the croſſe it threatens, as well as the Crown it promiſes; For ſo our Lord war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned his Diſciples, telling them, <hi>He that will come after me, and will be my Diſciple, must deny himſelf,</hi> (in his deareſt luſts &amp; ſins, nay, in his eſtate and life ſometime) <hi>and take up his Croſs</hi> (of afflictions and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution) <hi>and follow him,</hi> (in a way of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe &amp; purity in the ſtraight way.) And then he will give him <hi>a Crown of life,</hi> he ſhal have an hundred fold in this life, with perſecution (that is, the comfort of an hundred fold, if he miſſe of ſuch increaſe in the ſame kinde) and eternall glory in the World to come. Now we muſt ſit down &amp; conſider what we do, as (<hi>Luke</hi> 14.28.31) Chriſt teaches by the parable of him that builds a Tower, and of the King that goes to warfare. Now thus to chuſe our Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, to eſpouſe the Chriſtian Faith for bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, for worſe, to take the ſweat with the bitter, the Croſs with the Crown: This is another Act, wherein this choice ſtands.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Act is a ſetled purpoſe, and full reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution to live and dye therein, to adhere
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:101381:11"/>and cleave thereto, even to the end, to be faithful to the Death; to cleave to the Lord with full purpoſe of heart; as we read <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhua</hi> his reſolution, I and my houſe will ſerve the Lord; we are reſolved (who ever depart from <hi>Jehovah</hi>) we will cleave unto him. And as the Diſciples, <hi>John</hi> 6. when many forſook Chriſt and the Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion; their Lord ſaith unto them, and <hi>will ye alſo go away? Peter</hi> anſwers in the name of the reſt, <hi>whether ſhal we go, for thou haſt the words of Eternal life.</hi> Alack, if we draw back from the Lord, his ſoul ſhall have no pleaſure in us, we draw back unto perdition; but if we continue in the faith, we ſhal then have the Crown of life. Life and Death are before us herein, as <hi>Moſes</hi> told the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> if we ſerve the Lord and fear him and cleave unto him, then life; but if we turn from him, and his truth and wayes, then Death; all a mans righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe ſhal be forgotten, he ſhal dye in his ſins.</p>
               <p>Thus in theſe three Acts ſtands the right chuſing of a mans religion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:101381:11"/>
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Conſiderations evidencing it a principal point of wiſdom for a man to make a right choice of that Religion he profeſſes in the World, and ventures his Eternal Salvation upon.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>HAving ſhewed, wherein this wiſe chuſing ones Religion ſtands, and what Acts muſt concur thereto, We come next to demonſtrate it to be ſuch a princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal point of wiſedom for a man to make a right choice of his Religion he profeſſes in the world, and ventures his Salvation upon. This may be evinced from the enſuing Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The <hi>Neceſſity</hi> for a man to be of ſome Religion; and if ſo, wiſedom ſhould direct to make choyce of the beſt. Now it's ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to be of ſome Religion; We can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not live without God (<hi>Acts</hi> 17.28. <hi>In him we live, move, and have our being<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi>) And is it not fit then we ſhould acknowledge God and worſhip him? in the very framing of the nature of man, there are ſuch princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Religion ingraven in him, that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be razed out, that have taught the very Heathens to worſhip a Deity; ſo that we ſhould be worſe then Heathens, yea, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come very beaſts, and below men, if wee ſhould not be of ſome Religion: Beſides
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:101381:12"/>it is the expreſſe command of God, by his written Laws given to the Sonnes of Men, that they adore, worſhip and ſerve him; he expects it as an homage from them, and will not looſe his glory; Such Atheiſts are accurſed by him, as caſt off all Religion, &amp; live without God in the World: And though ſome ſuch Atheiſts have been found who in their proſperity forget God, whilſt they can better ſhift without him: yet in their miſeries and dangers, they have been forced to acknowledge God, and call upon him, as the Mariners in the Ship with <hi>Jonah, &amp;c.</hi> Now if it be ſo, Is it not fit to chuſe the true God, and the true Religion?</p>
               <p n="2">2. There are many falſe Religions in the World, and we may ſoon be impoſed on and deluded, if we make not a wiſe choice of our Religion; There be many Lords and many gods ſo called, (ſaith the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.5.) though to us, there is but one living and true God; ther's many wayes of Religion, Heatheniſm. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hometaniſm, Judaiſm, and Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; and amongſt Chriſtians, how many different wayes this day? ſcarce to be numbred, and therefore we had need to make a good choice. The greateſt part of the World were deceived in former
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:101381:12"/>times of old, the whole World almoſt fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed falſe gods, except <hi>Iſrael.</hi> At this day, ſome obſerve, if the World be divided into thirty parts, nineteen of them are Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Idolaters, ſix be <hi>Mahometans;</hi> ſome (though inconſiderable) <hi>Jews;</hi> and only the other five parts of the thirty be Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians: and how many different wayes be amongſt them? Proteſtants, Papiſts, <hi>Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covites, Greeks</hi> in <hi>Europe,</hi> (beſides multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes in other parts of the World,) And theſe admitting many ſubdiviſions amongſt themſelves; Therefore we had need to make a wiſe choice.</p>
               <p n="3">3. It's that whereupon our greateſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt depends; on the right chuſing ones Religion, or our miſtakes about it, eternall happineſs or miſery, life or death depend. <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.46, 47. in things of great im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance men uſe much deliberation, and make the wiſeſt choice they can, how ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary is it here? That opinion or dream that every man may be ſaved by his own Religion, if he be true to it, is more be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming <hi>Turks</hi> then <hi>Chriſtians.</hi> They ſay there are three Banners whereby men are conducted to Heaven, <hi>Moſes's, Chriſts,</hi> and <hi>Mahomets;</hi> but we Chriſtians know no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way to Salvation but one, <hi>viz.</hi> by faith in Jeſus Chriſt; <hi>for there's no other
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:101381:13"/>name under Heaven to be ſaved by, but by the name of Jeſus Chriſt, Acts</hi> 4.12. Indeed many leſſer differences may be amongſt them that hold that one Faith: They may hold the head Chriſt, and yet differ in ſmal things with ſafety to their Souls; if they build on the foundation and corner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone Jeſus Chriſt, (heartily believing the principles of the Chriſtian Faith, and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving according to them, though they add thereto the Hay, Stubble, and wood of ſmaller errors, they may be ſaved notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding theſe. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.15. Salvation may be had amongſt ſeveral forts of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, that all agree in the great Articles of the Chriſtian Faith, and live piouſly and charitably, whether <hi>Lutherans, Calviniſts, Arminians, Anabaptiſts, Epiſcopal, Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian, Independent, &amp;c.</hi> Theſe are not different Religions, but different forms of the ſame Religion, wherein the children of the ſame Father, are dreſſed up in different habits. But where any dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer in fundamentals, and even turn to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Religion, to another Goſpel, or Chriſt (as the Apoſtle ſpeaks to the <hi>Galatians,</hi>) as too many Sects amongſt us, are found to do, <hi>viz, Papiſts, Socinians, Quakers, &amp;c.</hi> Thoſe I mean who are throughly ſuch, not all that ignorantly adhere to
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:101381:13"/>them,) it would be fooliſh charity to flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter them with hopes of Salvation, in ſuch wayes, (if living and dying according to thoſe corrupt principles,) becauſe they are in the number of thoſe <hi>Damnable</hi> Hereſies the Scripture ſpeaks of. Now this being clear, that Salvation dependeth upon eſpouſing the right Religion; What wiſedom is it to make a good choice?</p>
               <p n="4">4. Becauſe elſe if one ſhould <hi>happen</hi> on the true Religion, he would never be <hi>True</hi> unto it, unleſs he take it up on ſuch a right choice, as before was ſpoken of; we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be <hi>Serious Chriſtians,</hi> nor <hi>through</hi> Chriſtians, but by halves only; nor <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant,</hi> holding out to the End, without this right choice.</p>
               <p n="1">(1.) <hi>Not ſerious Chriſtians.</hi> Such as take up a Religion they know not what, and on grounds they know not why, will be but ſleighty and formal in it; a little of outſide profeſſion they may have, but the power of it will be wanting. Thus the common ſort of Chriſtians, that take not up Religion on a wiſe choice, underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what it is, and diſcerning the verity and excellency of it, but becauſe it is profeſſed in the countrey where they live, injoyned by the Laws of the Land, and commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:101381:14"/>by the example of Others, whom they eſteem wiſe and holy, alack, how formal and ſleighty are they therein; not conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the glory of the great God that made them and redeemed them, is concerned therein, and that the Salvation of their own ſouls depends on it: Whereas ſuch as make a wiſe choice out of knowledge and diſcerning, ſerve God with all their heart and ſtrength and ſoul, they reſt not in the former, but labour in the power of godlineſſe. Religion is their main buſineſs in the World.</p>
               <p n="2">(2.) Nor <hi>thorough</hi> Chriſtians, but only by the halves, (as <hi>Agrippa, almoſt perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to be Chriſtians.</hi>) They will follow Chriſt a little way, and perform ſome of the out-ſide and eaſie parts of Religion: but when they hear ſome hard ſayings, (as the <hi>Capernaits</hi>) or ſome difficult duties preſſed on them that croſs fleſh and blood and worldly intereſt, they will except them, and ſay, <hi>in this thing the Lord be merciful to me,</hi> &amp;c. Theſe are like the <hi>Scribe, not farre from the Kingdome of Heaven, but never ſhall come there;</hi> like <hi>Herod,</hi> that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form many things, but not at all, will pick and chuſe where they pleaſe. Oh that this were not the caſe of many called Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians! And this becauſe they underſtand
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:101381:14"/>not aright what the Chriſtian Religion is, and take it not upon good grounds, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they fall ſhort: whereas he that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtands what an holy Religion it is, and what great duties it requires, and caſts up before hand the inconveniences, loſſes andl ſufferings he may meet with, comparing them with the recompence of reward, the far more exceeding and eternal weight of glory, he will go through-ſtitch, will fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low God fully, and will be altogether a Chriſtian.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Not <hi>Conſtant,</hi> but turning away from it upon every Temptation. Such are ever wavering and halting betwixt two, as the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> of old betwixt <hi>Iehovah</hi> and <hi>Baal.</hi> If hereſie, ſeducement, and the power of deluſions come amongſt ſuch, how do they turn away from that Religion they have imbraced by companies, and turn Runna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gados, or if the heat of perſecution ſcorch them, <hi>they wither away becauſe they have no Root. Mat,</hi> 13. We have had too ſad ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience of this amongſt the giddy unſtable ſort of Chriſtians in our times, when God had let looſe errors and hereſies amongſt us, (to try who were ſound and ſincere, and who not) how many were carried a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way as with a flood? And if <hi>Popery</hi> ſhould prevail again, or <hi>Mahometaniſm,</hi> through
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:101381:15"/>the conquering Sword of the <hi>Turks,</hi> one may tremble to think whither ſuch un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grounded Chriſtians may be carryed: <hi>Whereas</hi> on the other hand the Chriſtian that takes up his Religion on good grounds through a wiſe choice, knowing what, and in whom he hath believed, wil through grace ſtand ſtrongly <hi>as the Houſe built upon the Rock, Mat.</hi> 7. When the Winds blew and the Waves beat, he ſtands; <hi>The gates of Hell ſhall not prevail againſt ſuch.</hi> Therefore we ſee what a great point of wiſdom it is, for a man to make a wiſe choice of that Religion he takes up; elſe he will not be true unto it; he will not be a ſerious Chriſtian, nor a thorough, nor a conſtant Chriſtian, and then as good be none at all. It will nothing avail them unto Salvation to imbrace the true Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, no more then it did profite the <hi>Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites</hi> of old, to have the Temple of the Lord amongſt them; or the <hi>Philiſtims</hi> to have the Ark of the Covenant with them, it will but increaſe their condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Theſe conſiderations are ſufficient (without inſiſting upon any other) to evidence the truth of our propoſition, and to commend to us this great duty</hi> viz. <hi>The wiſe chuſing of that Religion we profeſſe in the World, that we
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:101381:15"/>mean to live and dye in, and to venture our Eternal Salvation upon.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Wherein the Practice of this Duty is inſiſted on, and Directions given how to chuſe the true Religion amongſt ſo many as are in the World. All other Religions being reje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, The Christian Religion is evidenced to be the only true Religion.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>WE are now come to the practicall part of our diſcourſe to ſhew how this may be reduced into action, that we have been treating on, but in <hi>words hitherto;</hi> let every one that God hath given the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of a man unto, be induced to make a wiſe choice of that Religion he ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures his eternal Salvation upon.</p>
               <p>This diſcourſe is intended only for ſuch as be reſolved to be of ſome Religion, and will not live as <hi>Atheiſts.</hi> As for them that will not be of any Religion at all, but live without God in the World, only live to eat and drink, and work and ſleap, and mind their ſenſual pleaſures, they degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate from the Nature of Men, and are even turned unto Beaſts; fooliſh are they and ignorant (to uſe the <hi>Pſalmiſts</hi> words, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73.) and even in this point as Beaſts, as far below men as <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> was
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:101381:16"/>when he did <hi>eat graſſe as the Oxen, and cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched amongſt the Beaſts,</hi> for ſuch violate the very Law of Nature, which hath taught all Nations, however rude and barbarous, to take up ſome profeſſion of Religion. They tranſgreſſe alſo the written Law of God, which he hath given in his Word, and will judge men by, at the laſt day, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires ſolemn worſhip and ſervice from the Sons of men. They bring themſelves directly under the curſe or imprecation, Jer. 10.25. <hi>Pour out thy fury upon the Heathen, and upon the Families that call not on thy Name. The wicked ſhall be turned into Hell, with all the Nations that forget God,</hi> Pſalm 9.17. As they ſay to God now, depart from us, we will not know thy wayes: ſo they ſhall hear God ſay to them ſhortly, <hi>Depart from me ye curſed,</hi> &amp;c. Nor do I ſpeak to ſuch baſe and low Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, as take up their Religion on truſt from others, and pinne their Faith upon the ſleeves of thoſe, to whom they have ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected their judgements and conſciences, upon account of any worldly, or corrupt intereſt: But to ſuch noble Spirits, as with the <hi>Bereans</hi> will take pains to fearch <hi>the Scriptures,</hi> and uſe all Gods appointed means to inform themſelves; that they may venture their ſouls on a ſure bottom.
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:101381:16"/>
                  <hi>Conſider</hi> as men, and make a wiſe choice of that Religion you venture your Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on upon. Its not ſufficient that it be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered to you by Tradition from your An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors; that you yave learned it by educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from Godly Parents; that it is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by the Laws of the Land where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you live, and commended by the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of wiſe and pious perſons, whom you reverence: but make a wiſe choice for your ſelves; Labour to underſtand di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctly the ſeveral Doctrines, and my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries of Faith, and duties of Godlineſſe contained therein: and to know the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and excellency of it; and ſo take it up upon deliberation, weighing both the conveniences and inconveniences ſo it, Comparing the ſufferings, loſſes, reproa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, perſecutions you meet withall: with the reward and Crown promiſed; and ſo make a wiſe choice of your Religion, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolving to live and dye therein, to adhere to it to the end, and be faithful even to Death.</p>
               <p>This is a duty neceſſary and ſeaſonable to be preſſed, ſome have not yet choſen their Religion. It's to be feared ther's too many, not only of the younger ſort, but of the more antient, who (according to the proverb) have their Religion to
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:101381:17"/>chuſe. Some have made ſome kind of choice, but need to be confirmed and eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed therein upon good grounds, and to be ſtirred up to be true to the true Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion they profeſſe, even to be ſerious, thorough and conſtant Chriſtians.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Make this choice then ſpeedily,</hi> for this is the buſineſſe you come into the World a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout, to know and acknowledge, to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and glorifie God; and your Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on depends upon it. Live not without God any longer, but acknowledge him that made and redeemed you, that feeds and preſerves you, and learn how to ſerve him acceptably. <hi>Do it wiſely,</hi> leſt you be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luded, there being ſuch <hi>diverſities</hi> of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligions, and ſo many falſe wayes in the World, you had need to have your eyes about you; erring herein will not ſtand with the ſafety of your ſouls, your exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal hapineſſe or miſery depends upon it. And then be <hi>True</hi> to that Religion you chuſe, play not faſt and looſe with it. It's a buſineſſe of higheſt concernment to be ſerious in Religion, what ever you trifle in, be not falſe herein, what ever you be faulty in. Let the Doctrines and myſteries of Faith you receive, influence your hearts and lives, ſanctify and change them; reſt not in the form of godlineſſe
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:101381:17"/>without the power of it. Men may as well miſcary in the true Religion as in a falſe, if they be falſe unto it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> But here a queſtion muſt be reſolved in order to the practice of this duty, which is this. <hi>Some may ſay, Seing there are ſuch diverſities of Religion in the World, How ſhal we be able to make a right choice, amongſt ſo many, of the true Religion, eſpecially ſuch of us as be weak and ignorant, when great and learned men differ ſo much about it amongst themſelves.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwer.</hi> This is a queſtion of very great importance, and indeed deſerves a ſerious Anſwer, I ſhal ſpeak to it in two par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars.</p>
               <p n="1">1. It is a miſtake to think, becauſe of the differences of opinions amongſt men, that there is ſuch a multitude of Religions in the World; for every different opinion is not a different Religion. There are (to ſpeak properly) but four Religions in the World, although there be different Sects &amp; parties amongſt each of theſe, <hi>viz. Heatheniſm, Mahometaniſm, Judaiſm and Chriſtianity.</hi> Indeed theſe four diſagree much amongſt themſelves. <hi>In Heatheniſm</hi> ſome worſhip one God, ſome another, ſome multitudes joyntly, as may beſeen in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and in all Hiſtories. In <hi>Mahometa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſm,</hi>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:101381:18"/>all follow that Impoſtor <hi>Mahomet,</hi> but yet there are great differences amongſt themſelves, ſo that they are at deadly Feud often one with another for their Religion ſake, as is ſtoried of the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> and <hi>Perſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Mahometans.</hi> In <hi>Judaiſm</hi> all worſhip the true God, the maker of Heaven and Earth, and receive the Law from <hi>Moſes,</hi> ſerving God according to the <hi>Ordinances thereof; yet have they different Sects</hi> amongſt themſelves, as the <hi>Phariſees, Sadducees, Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſens, &amp;c.</hi> In Chriſtianity all worſhip God in Chriſt, although there be diverſities of Sects and Hereſies amongſt them; So that indeed there are but four Religions in the world.</p>
               <p n="2">2. There's a great difficulty to diſcern which of theſe four we ſhould chuſe for our Religion, even the weakeſt underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding that indifferently weighs them, may be convinced.</p>
               <p n="1">(1.) For <hi>Heatheniſm,</hi> Its evident to rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon their Religion is not true, to worſhip ſo many Gods, and them alſo creatures, as the Sun and Moon, yea, mortal men that are dead, ſuch as <hi>Jupiter, Juno, Saturn, &amp;c.</hi> Yea, the worſt of Men, Their own Poets have branded them with black notes of infamy for Adultery, Theft, Murther, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> It was Gods juſt judgment (as the Apoſtle
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:101381:18"/>obſerves, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. <hi>To give them up to ſuch deluſions to worſhip ſuch gods, becauſe when they knew the true God they did not glorifie him as God.</hi> Many of their own Religion were convinced, they were not in the right, and therefore <hi>Cicero</hi> in his Book <hi>De naturâ Deorum,</hi> ſaith, <hi>I would I could as well finde out the true Religion, as convince others to be falſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">(2.) For <hi>Mahometaniſm,</hi> though it hath ſpread far over the World, (yea, further then <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> is ſpread at this day) yet its moſt eaſie to prove that to be a falſe Religion; Their Prophet was a deceiver and a very flagitious perſon, and wrought no miracles; their <hi>Alcaron</hi> is moſt barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and without ſenſe; their Doctrine impure as wel as their Lives; their Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on promiſes a carnal Paradiſe in the world to come, full of ſenſual pleaſures, not ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual, and ſuitable to rational immortal ſouls. It was propagated in the World by the Sword, and maintained by igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and ſuppreſſing all humane learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
               <p n="3">(3.) For <hi>Judaiſm,</hi> the third Religion in the World, That was indeed of God, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed in the Old Teſtament; But it was to continue for a time, till Chriſt came, <hi>of whom</hi> Moſes <hi>and the Prophets witneſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantly;</hi>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:101381:19"/>then at the time of Reformation it was to be aboliſhed, <hi>Heb</hi> 9.10. Their whole worſhip &amp; Ceremonies had reſpect to him on whom, becauſe they would not believe, but rej<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cted and crucified him, <hi>the wrath of God is come upon them to the utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt,</hi> They and their Temple was deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and the worſhip of it abrogated, and to this day ſo continues.</p>
               <p n="4">(4) It remains therefore that the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion is the true Religion, or elſe there's none in the World. And it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed is witneſſed to, both in <hi>Mahomets</hi> Alcoran, and in the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Old Teſtament, which ſpeaks fully of Jeſus Chriſt, his birth and parentage, with the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of time and place, his death, reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>&amp;c. This was confirmed by many ſignes and wonders, and real miracles wroght by the first planters of this Religion:</hi> Heb. 2.4  By the means and wayes of propaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> by weak and unlearned men, by whoſe preaching it ſoon overſpread the World and took ſuch rooting, that the power, craft, and malice of men and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils cannot root it out. Its evidenced by the purity and ſpirituality of its Doctrine; By the ſublimity of the Myſteries revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in it, wherein the higheſt wiſedom of God ſhines forth; By the greatneſſe and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:101381:19"/>excellency of the rewards &amp; puniſhments; By the holy Spirit appearing in the ſerious profeſſors of it (ſuch a Spirit of holineſſe as is no where elſe to be found in the world) And by the deſign it hath to glorifie God and to humble Man, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> By theſe and the like evidences the weakeſt, may eaſily be convinced, That the Chriſtian Religion is the only true Religion of all others in the World, and ſo be directed to make choice thereof.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Further Directions how to chuſe the right and ſafe way amongſt ſuch diverſities of Sects and opinions, as be amongst Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians. A diſcovery of the fundamental Doctrines of Faith and practical duties of Godlineſs, generally imbraced by al Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians in al times and places, with advice in reference unto them.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>HAving inquired into the ſeveral Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions this day profeſſed in the world<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and found upon good evidence the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion to be the only true Religion, men may venture their Salvation upon. Wee meet next with no ſmall diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty whereby weak and ignorant per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons are perplexed (occaſioned by the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:101381:20"/>diverſity of <hi>Sects</hi> and opinions which are found amongſt Chriſtians) <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Queſt.</label> To know, (after they once be reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to be Chriſtians) how to chuſe the right and ſafe way amongſt ſuch various Sects and different perſwaſions of thoſe called Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, (unleſs a man might be ſaved in any of theſe Sects and wayes) What directions are there for the ſafe conduct of ſuch as are at a loſſe herein?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Anſwer.</label> Becauſe this is a grand caſe wherein very many (in theſe ſad times of Diviſion) greatly need Direction, I ſhall guide them to a ſafe way, wherein they may ſecurely walk, and venture their Souls without fear of miſcarrying. And it is this; Let them labour to underſtand clearly and to imbrace heartily thoſe <hi>Fundamental &amp; Catholick verities of the Chriſtian Religion,</hi> which are more clearly laid down in the holy Scriptures, and have been owned by the Churches of Chriſt, generally in all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges &amp; places, ever ſince the Apoſtles times to our dayes, and tranſmitted to us in their Creeds, and Confeſſions of Faith, and are now owned by all (worthy the name of the Chriſtians) without diſpute, through all the Chriſtian World; let them ſo believe them, that they influence their Hearts and Lives throughly: And alſo
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:101381:20"/>all thoſe <hi>Confeſſed duties of godlineſs</hi> that all Chriſtians are agreed in, and walk up to the practice of them, and their Souls ſhall certainly be ſecured.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Know,</hi> that notwithſtanding theſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſities of <hi>Sects,</hi> and varieties of opinions which are found amongſt Chriſtians, from which they are not privileged (as neither are thoſe other three Religions, <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theniſme, Mahometaniſm, and Juda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſm,</hi> as before was ſhewed) nor ſhall be fully whilſt we be imperfect, and know but in part, and are in part carnall as well as Spiritual, whilſt the envious one ſhall fow Tares in the field of the Church, and it ſhall be the pleaſure of God to ſuffer theſe things to be, that they which are approved may be made manifeſt: Yet know, That there are ſome fundamentall and <hi>Catholick verities</hi> of the Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, which are <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, points gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally believed of all, having antiquity, uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſality, and conſent concurring with them; which the Scriptures call the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.10<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 11. <hi>The principles of the Doctrine of Chriſt,</hi> Heb. 6.1. <hi>The form of ſound words,</hi> 2 Tim. 1.13. Rom. 6.17. <hi>The proportion or Analogy of Faith.</hi> Rom. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 6. Which have been conveyed down from the Apoſtles, even to us in this laſt
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:101381:21"/>age of the World, <hi>nor could the gates of Hel ever prevail, ſo far as to extirpate them.</hi> And theſe are ſuch <hi>Confeſſed duties of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe,</hi> as none that have pretended to be Chriſtians have dared openly and directly to gainſay. Now theſe are the points that have greateſt influence on our hearts and lives, to ſanctifie and change them, and to promote the life and power of godlineſſe, (and rarely thoſe queſtions and matters of diſpute that are ſo hotly conteſted about) and theſe avail to the ſaving our Souls; up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our hearty imbracing and receiving theſe, or our renouncing of them, either in heart or life, depends our Salvation or Damnation. We had need therefore to ſet our hearts on theſe things, that we cordial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly believe theſe Doctrines, and practiſe thoſe Duties, and ſo doing we ſhall ſecure our eternal Salvation.</p>
               <p>Now for further improvement of this advice we ſhal more particularly inquire into theſe great and neceſſary Doctrines of faith and duties of godlineſs, and lay down ſome brief account of them in order to our belief and practice, and ſo conſequently to Salvation.</p>
               <p n="1">1. For the Fundamental Doctrines of the Chriſtian Religion. Not that I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take to give an exact account hereof; for
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:101381:21"/>to determine this (ſaith a learned man) <hi>is the master-piece of all the Divines in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendom; but only do declare thoſe truths, which being more clearly laid down in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, have been generally imbraced by all Churches worthy the Name of Chriſtians,</hi> (ſetting aſide controverted points) where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſo much truth is contained, as being joyned with holy obedience, may be ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to bring a man to everlaſting Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. This being premiſed they may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to theſe four <hi>Articles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">(1) Concerning God, That there is one God of an infinite, perfect, and ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all nature, Subſiſting in three moſt glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous perſons, <hi>the Father, the Sonne, and the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> who is the maker, preſerver &amp; Governor of all things, and intends his own glory in all his Works. That the greateſt concernment of reaſonable crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures is to know &amp; acknowledge this God, to fear, love, adore and glorify him, and their chief felicity ſtands in his love and favour, in fulleſt conformity to his Image, and neareſt communion with him, and in no earthly good ſeparate from him. This is one Article of Religion neceſſary unto Salvation to be known and believed, and not controverted amongſt Chriſtians. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve this throughly, and let it influence
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:101381:22"/>your hearts and lives, ſo as you ſtudy to know this God, and to get acquaintance with him, to fear, love, and ſerve him, to own him for your Soveraign Lord &amp; chief good.</p>
               <p n="2">(2) Concerning man, <hi>That God made man at the firſt in a very holy &amp; happy eſtate from which he ſoon fel through Satans Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, and all mankinde became plunged into ſin and miſery. That we are all hainous of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders againſt the God of Heaven, under his dreadful wrath and the curſe of the Law, barred out of Heaven and happineſs, and ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to eternal torments, if not ſpeedily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled to God and pardoned, and by renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing grace ſanctified and converted; which neither we, nor any meere creature is able to do for us.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>This is another Fundamentall Article of Faith,</hi> ſo clearly laid down in Scripture as it's beyond all controverſie. Entertain it not in the notion only, but let it be ſo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted, that you feel your ſin and miſery at your heart, and dare not to continue a day longer without reconciling and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doning mercy, and renewing and ſanctify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing grace, leſt you periſh; that you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpair of any creatures help, and feel your ſelves eternally undone, if the God of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven help not.</p>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:101381:22"/>
               <p n="3">(3) Concerning Jeſus Chriſt our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer. 

<hi>That the Lord Jeſus Chriſt the only begotten Son of God, coeſſential and coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal with his Father upon the appointment and deſignation of his Father, voluntarily undertook the office of a Saviour and Redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to Mankinde, &amp; being made Man, took on him our ſins, and the curſe of the Law, and giving himſelf up a Sacrifice and an offering to God for us, purchaſed by his death all things conducing to grace and glory: and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving by his own power ariſen from the dead and aſcended into heaven, he is become an al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficient Saviour, and will effectually confer pardon, grace and Salvation, on all thoſe who ſhal truly believe in him; And that there is no other name under Heaven to be ſaved by, but by the name of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>This is a great and neceſſary Doctrine of Salvation, ſo clearly held forth in Scripture, that it's beyond controverſie,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16. <hi>Let this Catholick verity be received not in the Nation only, but dwel in your hearts, that you may ſee the infinite worth and excellency of Jeſus Chriſt prize him as the only Savior, cloſe with him on all thoſe glorious accounts and end she was ſent upon by the Father, and yield up your ſelves to be ſaved by him in his own way, and upon his own Terms.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">(4) Concerning the application of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption.
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:101381:23"/>
                  <hi>That our Redeemer the Lord Joſus Christ having all power in Heaven &amp; Earth given to him, hath made a new Law or Covenant of grace &amp; cauſed it to be proclai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to the world, wherein he promiſes pardon and Salvation to all that ſhal ſincerely accept and own him for their Saviour and Lord Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer, and t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uly repenting of their ſins, ſhall reſt on his death and merits alone for life, &amp; love him above all things, and ſincerely obey his Goſpel. Laws and Commundments, &amp; ſhal perſevere in theſe duties to the end: And af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he ſhal have ſent his holy Spirit to work Faith and converſion in his Elect, He will certainly come again from Heaven in the glory of his Father with his mighty Angels, and by his mighty power ſhal raiſe the dead, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vene all both Quick &amp; dead before his Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Seat; and then ſuch as did truly repent them of their ſins, and ſincerely believed in his Name and obeyed his Goſpel, he will ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judge to Eternal glory and happineſſe with himſelf and his Father and the holy Angels: but unbelievers and impenitent perſons to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal torments in Hell with the Devil and his Angels.</hi> This is an unqueſtionable Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle of the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Faith, expreſly delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the holy Scriptures, and imbraced by the Catholick Church. <hi>Let this truth be received, not notionally but heartily; Let
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:101381:23"/>it influence your hearts and lives ſo as you ſincerely obey the Goſpel, and live in the day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly expectation of the coming of the Lord, and give deligence to be found of him in peace without ſpot, and blameleſſe.</hi> I ſhal add no other Doctrinal verities beſides theſe fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental Articles; They are the very ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the Chriſtian Creed imbraced by the Church in all ages and places</p>
               <p n="2">2. For thoſe <hi>Practical Duties</hi> in which all true <hi>Christians</hi> are agreed (for as there are in points of Faith fundamental Articles, ſo there are in the point of practice funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental Duties.) Now theſe are either.</p>
               <p n="1">(1) Thoſe Moral duties of the Law or Ten Commandements promulgated on <hi>Mount Sinai,</hi> and written by the finger of God in two Tables of ſtone, which <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians</hi> are obliged to obſerve as well as the <hi>Jews</hi> (though the Ceremonial Law, which was altogether typical and ſhadowed good things to come, be aboliſhed) Yea, wee are bound to keep it in a more ſtrict and ſpiritual manner then the <hi>Jews</hi> did inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret it formerly, as appears by Chriſts Sermon, <hi>Mat</hi> 5. This contains all duties of piety toward God, immediatly requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the firſt Table, <hi>viz.</hi> to take and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the God of Heaven that made us and gave us Life and breath, and beeing for
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:101381:24"/>our God alone; to know and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge him, to fear, love, and truſt in him, and ſeek his glory; to give him that exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal worſhip he requires in his Word, publick, private, and ſecret, as invoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his Holy Name by prayers and praiſes, hearing and reading, meditating and conferring on his Word, receiving his Sacraments, ſanctifying his Sabbaths: Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all this in an Holy reverent manner, ſo as Gods name may be ſanctifyed by us in his ordinances, as alſo in our ordinary communications and converſations. It likewiſe contains all Duties of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and charity towards Man, required in the ſecond Table, <hi>viz.</hi> The preſerving, as well as not injuring, of the honour and authority, of the life and chaſtity of our neighbour, in thought, word and deed; as alſo his eſtate, good name, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving him even as we love our ſelves, doing good unto all, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Theſe are general Duties, all Chriſtians are agreed in, Make Conſcience to practiſe theſe.</p>
               <p n="2">(2) Thoſe Evangelical Duties, or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements of the Goſpel. For beſides theſe Moral Duties of the Law which the Goſpel doth inforce alſo by renewed and more indearing arguments, there are peculiar duties required by the Goſpel, as
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:101381:24"/>True repentance for every ſin and tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion of Gods righteous and holy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands (for the Law gives no place to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, but threatens death for every offence.) Faith in the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, for pardon through his blood, and Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on through his merits: Fervent love to God and the Redeemer, who loved us and gave himſelf for us; who hath waſhed us in his blood, &amp; made us Kings and Prieſts to God and his Father; Sincere indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to promote his glory, upon the new obligation of Redemption; and living to him as his peculiar People, being not our own but his, bought with a price; Love to all the Saints and Members of Chriſt, and communion with them as we have opportunity, on account of that near union in Chriſt; which ſhould make us bear with ſmaller differences that do not violat the bond of union, whilſt they hold of Chriſt the head, and are of the ſame body, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe are confeſſed duties all Chriſtians are agreed in, Practiſe them Conſcionably. The Apoſtle gives us the ſum of all theſe together, <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.11, 12. <hi>The grace of God that bringeth Salvation, hath appeared to all men, teaching us to deny ungodlineſs and worldly luſts; and to live ſoberly, righteouſly and godly in this preſent world.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:101381:25"/>
               <p>This then is the Counſel I would give to ſuch as are reſolved to be Chriſtians, but are ſtumbled at the variety of opinions and perſwaſions amongſt the profeſſors of Chriſtianity, that they know not what to believe or what to practiſ: That they would believe thoſe fundamental and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick truths of the Chriſtian Religion, about which there is no diſpute amongſt us, and let them be ſo believed, that they influence their hearts and lives, and ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctify them: And alſo that they would conſcionably practiſe thoſe known and confeſſed duties, that all are agreed in, and then there will be no cauſe to queſtion their ſalvation and eternal happineſſe. But it is unſeaſonable to be contending violent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly about diſputable points of Faith, and external forms and modes of worſhip and diſcipline, and ſuch like queſtions about things not ſo clearly revealed in Scripture, no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> imbraced ſo generally by all true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians and Churches, nor indeed eaſie to be comprehended by the weaker ſort of Profeſſors; whilſt thoſe weighty things before nam'd, are neglected and diſregar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. Such will hardly evade the imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Hypocryſie, being ſo like the <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees,</hi> that Tithed <hi>Mint. Anniſe</hi> and <hi>Cummin,</hi> and neglected the weighty things of the Law.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:101381:25"/>
               <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Other Directions in points of a Secondary nature, that are not ſo clearly laid down in Scripture, nor unanimouſly received by all Chriſtians; but are <hi>Problematical,</hi> and yet there is a neceſſity to be of the one or other perſwaſion. How to make a right choice in ſuch a Caſe. <hi>Four Rules about this.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>But what, Are not the leaſt truths of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion worth contending for, and the ſmalleſt circumſtantials of Faith or wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip? Doth not God ſtand upon ſmal mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in his ſervice? Yes verily, in their due place, and after a Chriſtian manner, we may and ought to inquire after them. When we have yielded that Faith and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience that is due to the great and more neceſſary points of Salvation, We are then to ſtudy the mind of God in other things of a ſecondary and more inferior Nature; nor is the moſt minute truth to be deſpiſed or neglected by us. That therefore we may make a wiſe choyce of the true and right way in ſuch circumſtantial and leſſe neceſſary points, as truly pious and wife Chriſtians differ in, which are mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:101381:26"/>
                  <hi>non fideì ſed queſtìonum,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aug de peccat. orig.</hi> chap. 23.</note> (as St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſpeaks) not properly points of the <hi>Catholick Faith,</hi> but problematical and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſputable in the Church; and yet are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitated to be of the one or other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion: I come in the next place to give ſome directions about them; for which end, obſerve theſe few Rules which will be uſefull to us herein.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Humhly ſeek God by daily and fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent prayers and ſupplications to make his mind and will known to you herein; Lean not to your own underſtanding and wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, but confeſſe how weak you are, and full of error and darkneſſe; Beſeech him to take away the vail from before your eyes, to give you underſtanding, and teach you good judgment and knowledge; that what you ſee not, he would teach you, and wherein you are otherwiſe minded, he would reveal the truth unto you; Plead his promiſes of leading you into all truth, that you ſhall be all taught of God; that he will reveal his ſecrets to ſuch as fear him, and guide the meek in the way, and lead you by his Spirit. Hang upon the Lord daily for his guidance in ſuch difficult caſes as you are at a loſs in.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Search the Scriptures,</hi> John 5.39.
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:101381:26"/>and look well to them, they are your chard and compaſs to ſteer your courſe by, try all things by them, to the Law and to the teſtimony. Take nothing on truſt from men, for the beſt of men may err. I think there is hardly any error in Doctrine, or corruption in Worſhip, but hath been brought into the Church by following the opinions and practices of ſome reputed godly men, more then the Scriptures: when a <hi>Peter</hi> ſhall <hi>Judaize</hi> and not walk uprightly, he may not only ſeduce by his example many ordinary Chriſtians, but a <hi>Barnabas</hi> alſo may be carryed away from the truth by his diſſimulation, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2. Hold cloſe therefore to the Scriptures, thoſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible Oracles, the word of truth, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire daily into them.</p>
               <p n="3">(3) If yet after prayer and ſearching the Scriptures, we find not the minde of God inſome opinion or practice, (becauſe it is but darkly laid down in Scripture, or at leaſt through the darkneſſe of minde in godly men, who cannot ſo well diſcern it) Then obſerve this further Rule. There are ſome general <hi>criteria,</hi> or marks where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we may diſcern any Doctrine or practice whether it be of God or no; We ſhall find them laid down in the Scriptures, and may thereby try any Doctrine or practice,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:101381:27"/>when we can not ſo clearly ſee them in the particulars, <hi>viz.</hi> (1) Such Doctrines and practices as are not repugnant to, but agree and correſpond with the fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Articles of the Chriſtian Religion, or the firſt principles, that be according to the proportion or Analogy of faith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.6. They be of God, receive and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace them; but if they be not conſonant thereunto, then reject them. (2) Such Doctrines and practices as tend to holineſs, <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.2. Doctrines according to godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, they are of God, for he is a God of holineſs, follow them: But ſuch as tend to looſeneſſe and profaneſs are to be ſhun'd as not of God. This mark diſcovers the evil of ſuch opinions as teach men to caſt off Sabbaths, Ordinances, Scriptures, family and cloſet devotions, and other libertine principles; yet here beware on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary of a pretended holineſſe above what is written, of being righteous over much, above and beyond the rule of the word, this was the occaſion of Monkiſh or ſolita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry living amongſt the Papiſts, of their pretended holy Orders, Vows, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And amongſt others it hath cauſed Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Superſtition and many other irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular Actings.</p>
               <p n="3">(3) Such Doctrines and waies as tend
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:101381:27"/>not to diviſion and faction, but to peace, love, and union amongſt ſuch as fear God, thoſe are of God, and to be followed by us, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.10. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.1, 2. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.3, 4, 5, 6. But the contrary to be ſhunned and avoided, <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.17.</p>
               <p n="4">(4) Such things as tend to edification, and to further the Salvation of our ſouls, are to be received as of God, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.26. <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.19. But thoſe things that Miniſter Queſtions and cauſe ſtrife and contention, rather then godly edifying, are to be avoided, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.4, 5.</p>
               <p n="5">(5) Such Opinions and practices as tend to the glory of God and of Jeſus Chriſt, and to the ſetting up his righteouſneſs and grace, and to the humbling and debaſing of man, and caſting him down from all high thoughts of his own excellency and abilities, they are to be received as from God; for this is the great deſign of the Goſpel, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. <hi>a fin,</hi> but the contrary is to be rejected.</p>
               <p>Theſe general <hi>Criteria</hi> or Marks may be ſome guide to find out the right and ſafe way in ſome Doctrines and Practices that you are at a loſs in, becauſe you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not read them ſo plainly in the word of God.</p>
               <p>Rule 4, After you have thus done the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:101381:28"/>utmoſt you are able, to find out the mind of God in theſe controverted matters, which yet are diſputable amongſt the wiſe and godly, and you ſhall be neceſſitated to be of the one or the other perſwaſion or way; Then let every one do that which he is fully perſwaded in his own minde to be beſt and moſt pleaſing to God; nor dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to go againſt the dictates of his own Conſcience,
<note place="margin">See <hi>Ameſ Caſ.</hi> l. 1. c. 5 q. 1. <hi>Sanderſ. Lect</hi> 3. <hi>de juram.</hi> Sect. <hi>10.</hi>
                  </note> which God hath ſet up as his Vicegerent in the Soul, nor ſubjecting himſelf to the judgment or Authority of any other, as Lord of his Faith; I ſay Believe and imbrace that opinion, and walk in that practice; But yet to this. (1) Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly with a due ſenſe of your own weakneſs and ignorance, not proudly cenſuring and contemning ſuch as differ from your perſwaſion, but ever ready to hear what ſhall be offered for your conviction, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially if it be from the wiſe and learned, and thoſe which by Gods providence are in place of eminency in the Church; being rather matter of Affliction to you, then of exalting your ſelf that you ſhould differ from them.</p>
               <p n="2">(2) Peaceably and without all Faction and Schiſm, not making parties for you,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:101381:28"/>and renting from the Communion of thoſe with whom you agree in the moſt weighty and neceſſary Doctrines of Salvation, and ſo diſturbing the peace of the Church where you live: The evil of which can never be repaired by a violent contention for any truth or practice not fundamental and neceſſary unto Salvation. Here the counſel of the Apoſtle is ſeaſonable, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14 <hi>If thou haſt faith, have it to thy ſelf,</hi> and <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. <hi>Whereto we have already attained, let us walk by the ſame rule, let us minde the ſame thing, &amp; if in any thing any be otherwiſe minded, God wil reveal even this unto them.</hi> In all thoſe principal points of faith and practice, wherein is ſuch perfect harmony, it's a manifeſt duty to hold communion, only forbearing the ſame in theſe leſſer matters, wherein according to the preſent apprehenſion the ſin and error lyeth.</p>
               <p n="3">(3) Chearfully and confidently, not troubling and perplexing your ſelves about ſuch a perſwaſion and practice, with fears ariſing from a ſcrupulous Conſcience, (which are like Stones in the ſhooe, trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling the Feet of him that walketh;) But with a comfortable perſwaſion that God is well pleaſed with you, ſeing you do the utmoſt you are able, to find out the minde of God in ſuch a particular; and therefore,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:101381:29"/>if you be in the right, he will accept it; or if through weakneſſe there be a miſtake, yet he will graciouſly pardon it, and in his good time reveal even this unto you. For if even earthly Parents or Maſters, when their Servants or Children do their utmoſt to know their minds, and to do their buſineſs, ſo as to pleaſe them, will accept their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours, and take all in good part, though in every <hi>punctìlio</hi> they have not done what was expected: much more will the graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous God accept of his Children and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, that deſire to pleaſe him, and pardon what is amiſs in them. And indeed if not, no fleſh living could be ſaved: for who is there of the higheſt form of Chriſtians, that are aſcertained, that in every particular Doctrine and Practice (in thoſe things controverted amongſt the godly and wiſe) that they be in the right? ſeeing the beſt of men are imperfect, and may, and do err &amp; offend. Therefore go on chearfully with full aſſurance that the Lord accepts you, This Rule the Apoſtle fully layes down, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14 upon occaſion of controverſies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout points not neceſſary to Salvation, <hi>viz.</hi> Meats and Drinks and Dayes. He bids, let every one be fully perſwaded in his own mind, and act accordingly; not judging and condemning others, nor breaking the peace<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:101381:29"/>and then he ſhould be accepted of God, &amp; approved of men. Thus have we a ſafe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct to lead us in the right way in matters circumſtantial, controverted amongſt pious and wiſe Chriſtians, in points leſs neceſſary unto Salvation; as well as in matters of Fundamental, and of abſolute neceſſity thereunto.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>A cloſer Application of the foregoing Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, to the preſent State of the Church in <hi>England;</hi> with particular Advice in reference to the different Wayes and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions found amongſt us.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>HAving given a more generall advice ſutable to all times and conditions of the Church in all places: It will be expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent next (in behalf <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f thoſe for whoſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite this diſcourſe is principally intended) to apply the former directions, to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſtate of the Church here in <hi>England,</hi> and thoſe many different Perſwaſions and wayes that are amongſt us.</p>
               <p>We are a people that generally do pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs the Chriſtian Religion, which hath been of long time tranſmitted down to us from our Anceſtors: wherein we are deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ingaged by Education, the Laws of the Land, and manifold Obligations<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But it is
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:101381:30"/>much to be deſired that the Common ſort of Chriſtians, were better inſtructed in the grounds and Reaſons of the entertainment of this Religion (rather then of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther three before mentioned, <hi>Heatheniſm, Mahometaniſm,</hi> and <hi>Judaiſm,</hi>) and that they might gain a clear and diſtinct know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the great and fundamental Articles thereof, and be throughly grounded in the certainty and excellency of it; A thing which is much wanting in the vulgar ſort through their too great negligence and careleſneſſe about things ſpirituall: but of exceeding dangerous conſequence to their Souls, as expoſing them to profaneneſs and Error, if not to totall Apoſtacy. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this duty (though before hinted) de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves to be reinforced with the ſtrongeſt perſwaſions.</p>
               <p>But although we all be Chriſtians in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, We are ſadly crumbled into ſuch Diverſities of Sects and perſwaſions, occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned much through the licentiouſneſſe of War, &amp; relaxation of Government amongſt us of which occaſion Satan and our corrupt natures have made too great improvment; That is it moſt difficult for weak and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant perſons to find out the right and ſafe way amongſt them, and to joyn themſelve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> unto; This temptation having led very
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:101381:30"/>many into errors by-wayes &amp; pernicious, and others into <hi>Atheiſm.</hi> We ſhall there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore attempt to give ſome directions what courſe to ſteer herein; what opinions and Sects to ſhun and avoid: and what people and principales we ſhould cloſe withal. For it would greatly conduce to the peace and welfare of the Church, and to the ſafety of mens ſouls, to be duly informed, <hi>What Chriſtians (or Societyes of Chriſtians) they be, with whom communion may be held, and how far; as alſo who they be that are utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be avoided:</hi> it being uſual with the vulgar ſort of Chriſtians, who ſometimes abound in zeal, but are much wanting in knowledge, to cloſe with the moſt perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Principales and Wayes, where any ſtronger temptations inſinnate themſelves; then with thoſe that are far more ſound and Orthodox, if they have taken up a prejudice againſt them, and ſo have the faith of Chriſt with reſpect of perſons. We ſhall therefore take a Survey of the different perſwaſions &amp; wayes amongſt us which may be branch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into theſe two. 1. The Way &amp; profeſſion which is publickly owned by Authority, and hath the Law of the Land for its San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. 2. Thoſe Perſwaſions, or Wayes, that are taken up by private perſons con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ary to the Law of the Nation.</p>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:101381:31"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>For theſe latter</hi> (beginning there firſt) They are, as exceeding many, ſo of a very different nature; ſome retaining the Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental Principles and Duties of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, neceſſary unto Salvation, and differing only in leſſer matters, controverted in the Church of Chriſt: others that overthrow the very Foundation it ſelf.</p>
               <p>Thoſe that overthrow the Foundations of Chriſtianity, and differ about points ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary unto Salvation, are too many.</p>
               <p>In which rank we ſhall place the Papiſts firſt of all, becauſe moſt conſiderable, and above all others moſt formidable. Its true indeed, There hath been in the Popiſh Church, all a long to this day, continued ſuch a Syſtem of ſaving Truths (which God hath of his great mercy preſerved in the greateſt <hi>Anti Chriſtian Apoſtacy</hi>) as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing truly believed and obeyed (other Soul-deſtroying errours in the mean time, either not known or not cordially imbraced,) might be effectuall to the Salvation of many that lived and dyed within that Church: But yet Popery it ſelf, underſtanding thereby that Religion which conſiſts of ſo many new Articles of Faith (utterly unknown to the old Church of <hi>Rome</hi> in its purity, but now ratifyed in the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> and required to be recieved of all men upo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:101381:31"/>pain of <hi>Anathema</hi>) which plainly over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw many of the great Articles of the <hi>Catholick</hi> Faith; as alſo of ſuch groſſe I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatries and Superſtitious Fopperies <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This, <hi>I</hi> ſay, is ſuch a Religion, that none that love their Salvation ſhould cloſe with. This <hi>Babylon</hi> we ſhold have no communion with, leſt we communicate in her Plagues. As ſaith the voice from Heaven, <hi>Revel.</hi> 18 4. <hi>Come out of her my people, that ye be not partakers of her ſins, and that ye receive not of her plagues.</hi> The grounds of our with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawing from that Religion, are 1. Their many dangerous errors in matters of Faith, overthrowing directly the very Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Chriſtiantie. To inſtance in ſome Their Doctrine of Tranſubſtantiation, over-throweth the truth of Chriſts humane Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; Their proper Sacrifice, his only Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice for ſin offered once for all; Their Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of merits plainly deſtroyeth the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rins of Jeſus Chriſt: The multitude of Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diators amongſt them, deny That only Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator betwixt God and man, the man Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt; 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.5. Their Sacrificing Prieſts overthrow Chriſts Prieſtly office. Their vilifying the Scriptures, and ſetting up their unwritten Traditions to be recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved with equall reverance with them, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Overthrows Chriſts Propheticall Offices.
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:101381:32"/>The Kingly Office of Chriſt, is overthrown by the Popes uſurpations, diſpenſing with the Laws of God, and ſetting up other Laws of his own deviſing, and Lording it over the Conſciences of Men. The great Article of Remiſſion of ſins, and free Juſtification, through the grace of God in Jeſus Chriſt, is overthrown by their Pardons, Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences and Doctrine of merit, and humane Satisfactions. 2. Their abominable Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries in point of Worſhip, as Angel-wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, Saint-worſhip, Relique-worſhip, I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage-worſhip, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 3. Their prophane Sacriledge, robbing the people of the bread of life, the holy Scriptures: the Cup in the<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Lords Supper; Nay almoſt, of the whole Worſhip of God, cauſing it to be performed in a Language the Vulgar underſtand not. 4. Their cruelty and blood ſhed, wherein <hi>Rome</hi> Papal exceeds <hi>Rome</hi> Ethuicall. 5. Their Spiritual Tyranny in exacting blind obedience in matters of Faith, as the <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtims</hi> pulled out the eyes of <hi>Sampſon,</hi> and led him whither they would: In burden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Chriſtians with innumerable Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies and Superſtitions, deſtroying the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of Religion, 6. Their proud uſurpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions over Kings and Princes. 7. The No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious Schiſm they are guilty of, (worſe then that of the <hi>Novations</hi> and <hi>Donatiſts</hi> of
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:101381:32"/>old) whereby they not only caſt off the Reformed Churches; but the <hi>Muſcovites</hi> and <hi>Grecians</hi> in <hi>Europe,</hi> The <hi>Aegyptian</hi> and <hi>Aethiopian</hi> Churches in <hi>Affrick,</hi> &amp; all theſe great companies of <hi>Chriſtians</hi> ſcatter'd all over <hi>Aſia</hi> even from <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> to the <hi>Eaſt Indies;</hi> Becauſe they are not the Popes ſubjects, they wil not account them Chriſts; for they declare, determine and pronounce, its of abſolute neceſſity unto Salvation, for every humane Creature to be ſubject to the Pope of <hi>Rome.</hi> 8. Add hereunto, their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufferable wickedneſſe, overſpreading that Church, and their allowance thereof by gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Licences to uncleanneſs, <hi>Sodomy,</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituting pardons for mony, diſpenſations with Gods Laws, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> In all which the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church is incorrigible, pretending unerring Infallibilitie, and the Pope him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf wil be ſupreme Judge alone in all theſe Caſes. For theſe and the like grounds (which cannot all be here enumerated) Its neceſſary for all good Chriſtians to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of Popery, and have no Peace with <hi>Rome,</hi> till ſhe return to her antient Primitive puritie.</p>
               <p>Others there are alſo that err in Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental points and neceſſary unto ſalvation, as <hi>Anti-trinitarians, Anti-Scripturiſts, Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:101381:33"/>Socinians,</hi> &amp;c. The laſt of which Sects is eſteemed by the learned, the very Sink into which all Hereſies of former and lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter times have emptied themſelves, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly leades men to <hi>Mahometaniſm, Juda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſm,</hi> or <hi>Atheiſm.</hi> Theſe deny the Doctrine of the Trinity (a fundamental Point, and neceſſary to Salvation) and the Deity of Jeſus Chriſt, and of the Holy Ghoſt, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject the Satisfaction of Chriſt, and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Juſtification by works; Refuſe ſuch Articles of the Faith, as they cannot com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend with their Reaſon, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Theſe Sects as almoſt all Churches (former and latter) and Divines in their <hi>Syncretiſms,</hi> have bani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed out of the Lines of Chriſtian Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication: ſo it becomes all perſons to avoid them as peſts, and enemies of Chriſtianity, and to have no followſhip with them. I ſhal inſtance only in one Sect more<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of ſuch as err in Fundamental points; who in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of their want of learning and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward accompliſhments, are contemptible; yet in reſpect of their number and their ſingular obſtinancy in their way, whereby they amuſe the Vulgar, are not to be paſſed by <hi>viz.</hi> The Quakers, although Quake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſm cannot properly be called a Séct of Chriſtians, but rather it's a totall Apoſtacy from Chriſtianity; for excepting it be they
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:101381:33"/>have the name of Chriſt in their Mouths, they ſcarce retain any Article of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Faith. The light in all men they extoll, as the only ſufficient rule to walk by, to the apparent ſlighting of the Scriptures and Preaching; ſo that if the Queſtion be as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, what advantage hath the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the naked <hi>Indian?</hi> We cannot an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer as the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.2. <hi>Much e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very way?</hi> chiefly, becauſe <hi>unto them is committed the Oracles of God.</hi> The Doctrine of the Trinity they openly deny; The Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of Jeſus Chriſt, as to his humane Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, with all his Offices aſſigned to him by his Father, they utterly reject, (though this is an <hi>Arcanum</hi> that is kept hid from their Novices.) They call not upon God in the Name and Mediation of Jeſus Chriſt; They truſt not in his death for pardon and Salvation, but in a pretended ſinleſs perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; they deny any neceſſiy of the Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial grace of the Spirit to Converſion and Sanctification, ſaying,
<note place="margin">I charge not every particular quaker with all theſe Errours (for many underſtand not what they hold) But mention what I finde aſſerted in their prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Pamphlets.</note> the Light within them is ſufficient hereunto, and ſcoff at them that pray for more; bidding them heed that only, and it will lead them from ſin to God. Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:101381:34"/>and Sacraments, and all inſtituted Worſhip they caſt off; the great Doctrines of the Reſurrection, Laſt Judgement, Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Hell they turn into Allegories, &amp;c. Theſe, and other things conſidered, it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears that they plainly overthrow the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations of Chriſtianity, &amp; therefore Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans can have no Communion with that way.</p>
               <p>Thus where differences are in Points deſtructive to the Foundations of Religion, and againſt the Eſſentials of Faith, worſhip and obedience: There can be no cloſure and agreement, but a total withdrawing, is neceſſary ſo far as civil Relations and Offices will permit.</p>
               <p>We come next to conſider theſe other Perſwaſions and Parties among us, that (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeing in all the neceſſary points of Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, yet) differ in things that be leſs ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary; though ſome be of greater, and ſome of leſs moment then others Theſe dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences be either in Points of Doctrine, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n matters of Worſhip and Diſcipline. In Poi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ts o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Doctrine we have <hi>Arminians, Antinomians, &amp;c.</hi> In matters of Worſhip and Diſcipline, we have <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> (I mean ſuch as be ſound in the main Doctrines of faith, but err only in the point of Baptiſm) <hi>Independents, Presbyterians. &amp;c.</hi> Now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout theſe differing wayes, Take theſe brief
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:101381:34"/>Directions ſutable to thoſe generall Rules before lay'd down.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Account them all as Chriſtians, if they be ſerious in the matters of Religion, and their lives anſwerable; let not any evil re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentations of their opinions or waves, or odious and invidious conſequences drawn from their Principles, but diſowned by them, ſo far alienate your hearts from them, as not to account them Chriſtians &amp; Brethren; ſeeing they retain the Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentals of Chriſtianity and hold the head Chriſt, though they build on the precious Foundation, Wood, Hay, Stubble. Who is in all things free from Errour? What Church or perſon upon Earth?</p>
               <p n="2">2. Have the greateſt reſpect, and the moſt intimate friendſhip for thoſe in whoſe Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples is greateſt purity, that come nigheſt the rule, and who moſt follow after peace &amp; holineſſe, and lay out themſelves more to promote the greateſt truths of the Goſpel, and the power of Godlineſſe, then their pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate perſwaſions: But as for them who with the Wilde fire of their Zeal, will ſet the Church on a flame, and are more for making Proſelytes for their own way, then for ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the welfare of the Church, and the edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication and Salvation of ſouls, avoid them.</p>
               <p n="3">3. If God caſt your lot into theſe places
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:101381:35"/>or Countreys, where thoſe Profeſſions or Wayes are ſet up; &amp; you cannot enjoy that way of ſerving God, that you approve as moſt pure; its an unque<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>inable duty to hold Communion there, in <hi>France</hi> &amp; <hi>Holland</hi> with the Presbyterians, in <hi>Germany</hi> with the <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therans;</hi> &amp; in other Countreys with thoſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther perſwaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s before named; provided the condition of thy communion be not to give thy allowance to any thing that is evil, but in that particular thou mayeſt be forborn<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Communion with ſuch Churches where many corruptions and abuſes are, (if the foundations of faith, and eſſentials of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip be preſerved) ought to be maintained, with a due care to keep our ſelves only from the ſins of ſuch a Church, elſe the Apoſtle would have enjoyned ſeparation from the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> for the corruptions found there; and the Novatians, Donatiſts<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and others in the antient Church were un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtly taxed, for withdrawing from her Communion for laxneſs of Diſcipline, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther corruptions which they apprehended to be therein. This duty our Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> hath taught by her own practice, who hath ever owned the reformed church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es beyond Sea for <hi>Siſter-Churches,</hi> &amp; given them the right hand of Fellowſhip; though differing from her in ſome matters of an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour nature.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:101381:35"/>
               <head>CHAP. VIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Wherein the great controverſies of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with, or Separation from the Church of <hi>England</hi> is diſcuſſed. A view of what is therein praiſe-worthy, and what is diſallowable in the judgment of thoſe that ſcruple Communion. Directions ſuted thereunto.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>WE have ſpoken of thoſe different wayes and perſwaſions found a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt private perſons without, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the owning and approbation of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, and given advice in reference to them: We are next to conſider of that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſſion publickly ſet up by Authority, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat hath the civil Sanction of the Laws of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>his Land.</p>
               <p>No ſober perſon can gainſay, But this deſerves a moſt ſerious and impartial con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration; partly in reſpect of that Duty we owe to thoſe in Authority, to whom God hath committed the care of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and the ſettling of it in their Dominions, in ſuch a way as they think moſt agreeable to the Rule of the Word, and hath injoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed us obedience to them in the Lord; partly in reſpect of our own welfare, who may elſe ſuffer the penalty of the Laws, and had need to ſee to it, if we obey, that we
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:101381:36"/>do it with a good Conſcience, and if we ſuffer, that we ſuffer for the Truth, and not as evil doers; And partly in reſpect of the peace and welfare of the Church, that we do not groundleſly make a Rent therein, and thereby (as much as in us lyeth) to procure the ruine thereof, for all Diviſion tends to Deſtruction,</p>
               <p>It would therefore ſeriouſly be inquired, Whether it be a duty for Chriſtians to hold Communion with the Church of <hi>England</hi> according to its preſent ſtate and admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations? or, Whether Separation from it, is warrantable and neceſſary, and how far?</p>
               <p>For the Reſolving of which Queſtion, we ſhal take an Account of thoſe things that are commendable in the ſaid Church in the judgment of thoſe that ſcruple Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with her; and alſo of what things they diſallow and diſlike in her: And then caſt up, Whether it will warrant ſeparation, or how far, according to the ſame Rules of Concord we have proceeded upon, with thoſe of the other Profeſſions before named</p>
               <p>And firſt, it will not be denyed by all Diſſenters (that have underſtanding and ſobriety in them) But that here is to be found (1.) A clear profeſſion of all thoſe Fundamental points of Faith, which are accounted amongſt Chriſtians neceſſary
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:101381:36"/>unto Salvation; yea ſuch a poor Confeſſion of other points of a Secondary, and more inferiour Nature, as that there's ſcarce any other Church in the World, that God hath bleſſed with a greater purity in point of Doctrine then the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">(2.) Here alſo is the Chriſtian Sabbath imbraced with much greater honour then in many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Reformed Churches;
<note place="margin">Homily of time and place of Prayer. Part 2.</note> the publick Ordinances of preaching Prayer, Sacraments, adminiſtred and all the Subſtantials of Worſhip owned <hi>viz.</hi> That God only is to be Worſhipped &amp; no Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, Saints, or Angels; That he is to be Worſhipped only in and through Chriſt as our only Mediator and Advocate; that he is to be Worſhipped in Spirit &amp; truth, &amp; to be Sanctifyed of them that come near unto him</p>
               <p n="3">(3) As for Fundamental Duties and Points of Practice, here is a Profeſſion of Faith in Jeſus Chriſt alone, for Salvation; of Repentance from dead works, and love to Jeſus Chriſt, and to all that are his; and obedience to the Moral Law of the Yen Commandements. Here is a profeſſed Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuntiation of the Devil, the World, and the fleſh, with all their ſinful works and Luſts. All theſe call for an ingenuous and candid acknowledgment. How would our
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:101381:37"/>fore-Fathers that lived in former times of Popery, have rejoyced to have ſeen ſuch things in <hi>England?</hi> We ſhould breſſe God that hath vouchaſed ſuch a mercy to us; Honour our Defender of the Faith, under whoſe protection this Profeſſion is made; and ſhew more Reverence to the Church then many do, who will pettiſhly ſlight all this, becauſe they have not all they would have.</p>
               <p>Secondly, we are next to conſider thoſe things that are diſliked by ſuch as ſcruple Communion; which are eſpecially redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible to three Heads. (1.) Government and Diſcipline, which though it be various in the Reformed Churches, yet notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they hold mutual Communion with each other, as Siſter-Churches; and many particular wiſe and godly Members of thoſe Churches hold Communion in the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of God adminiſtred in the Churches of different wayes, occaſionally when they reſide amongſt them.</p>
               <p n="2">(2.) Forms of Prayers and Ceremonies, concerning which ſome diſallow all ſet and impoſed forms whatſoever; others only diſlike the form by law eſtabliſhed, account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it inconvenient, diſorderly and defective, and rejecting the Ceremonies: yet wiſe and ſober perſons generally (Non-Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſts
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:101381:37"/>as well as Conformiſts) reckon ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal forms and modes of Divine Service, not of the Eſſentials of Worſhip; but ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juncts thereunto belonging,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ameſ Caſ</hi> l. 4. c. 14 &amp;c. 17. <hi>Preſtons daity Exerciſe.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>E. G.</hi> The Eſſence of Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er lies in lifting up true de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires to God in the name of Chriſt, for things agreeable to his will, in the elevation of the heart or mind to God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Words are but the outward clothing of theſe deſires and holy affections, or the Chariot wherein they mount up to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. And for the Ceremonies uſed in <hi>England,</hi> they are utterly denied to be any parts of Worſhip, and declares only circumſtantial appendants thereunto (ſee the Preface to the Common Prayer, and Canons, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">(3.) Corruption in manners, and that both in People and in Miniſters, which when found in the latter, makes the offence far greater, as when the Sons of <hi>Eli</hi> were wicked, they made the offerings of the Lord to be abhorred. Theſe things pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, We ſhall now offer our advice in this great Controverſie, and annex ſuch Reaſons thereto, as ſhall evidence it both ſafe and profitable; We lay it down in three particulars.</p>
               <p n="1">1. To beware of a Total withdrawing
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:101381:38"/>from the publick Aſſemblies in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and the worſhip of God there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in (whilſt the Fundamentals of Faith, and eſſentials of Worſhip are therein maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned) becauſe you apprehend therein ſome corruptions, defects, additions, or errors which are circumſtantial.</p>
               <p>This advice though it might be urged with manifold arguments, yet the Brevity I intend in this Diſcourſe, requires me to give but a few.</p>
               <p n="1">(1.) If you will make the Scripture your Rule herein, you may ſee ſo clear a Beam of Light (all along through the ſame) witneſſing hereunto, That it is a wonder any ſhould be found to Queſtion this duty. Conſider the Prophets and people of God in the time of the Old Teſtament, did they ſeparate from the true Worſhip of God in the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Church (or teach any to do it) when there were very great defects &amp; cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions therein? There was at ſome times a defect of ſome Solemn Ordinances for a long time together, as Circumciſion, the Paſſeover, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Some Monuments of Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry remaining amongſt them, and the People (many of them) defiled there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with; Very great corruptions of manners, not only in the People, but in the Prieſts, as in <hi>Eli</hi>'s Sons, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Yet whilſt the true
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:101381:38"/>Worſhip of God was continued amongſt them, there's neither precept or practice to be found of total withdrawing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>from. Indeed the godly <hi>Levites</hi> &amp; People did withdraw from the Idolatrous Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of <hi>Jereboams Calves,</hi> leaving their dwellings and going to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> 2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 11.14, 16. but no mention is made of with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawing from the true Worſhip of God for ſuch cauſes as were before named.</p>
               <p>About the time of our Saviour Chriſt, and his Apoſtles, the State of that Church was greatly corrupted (by many degrees more then any ſober perſon can judge the preſent Church in this Nation now to be) The Interpreters of the Law had taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the Key of knowledge, and that little knowledge that remained, was miſerably corrupted, not only with the Leaven of the <hi>Phariſees,</hi> but with the damnable Hereſie of the <hi>Sadducees;</hi> The Worſhip of God much prophaned and the Temple polluted and made a Den of Theeves; A multitude of Superſtitious Ceremonies introduced that were a burden too heavy to bear; The power of godlineſs ſubverted, whilſt ſmall things were exactly minded, the weighty things of the Law as Judgment and the love of God were neglected; a general over ſpreading of ſin, not only amongſt the Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:101381:39"/>but the Prieſts themſelves, and that in their Miniſtration and calling, as well as in their Lives, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Yet did not the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly withdraw from the Communion of that Church for the ſame. We read that <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meon, Anna,</hi> and Others continued in the Temple Worſhipping God daily; Holy <hi>Zachary</hi> forſook not his Prieſtly Office, but Miniſtred in his courſe in the Temple; And Chriſt himſelf was circumciſed, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to the Lord in the Temple with the accuſtomed Sacrifices offer'd for him, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Law of <hi>Moſes;</hi> he kept the Paſſeover, and other Feaſts of that Church, was frequently in the Temple, and in the Synagogues with his Diſciples, allowed of the hearing of thoſe that ſate in <hi>Moſes</hi>'s Chair (only gives caution againſt their Errours and bad lives) ſent divers to the Prieſts to Offer their accuſtomed Off<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rings, required in the Law; Nor did he in the dayes of his fleſh wholly forſake the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of that Church; nor his Diſciples after him, untill the <hi>Jews</hi> did contradict and blaſpheme the Truth, obſtinately refuſe to owne the Lord Jeſus for the Chriſt, and perſecute to death the Profeſſors of the Name of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>In the Churches of <hi>Corinth, Galatia,</hi> &amp;c. We read of great and dangerous Errors in
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:101381:39"/>Faith, grievous pollutions in Worſhip, &amp; ſad miſcarriages in Manners: yet concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing withdrawing from theſe Churches, we find not a word; but many reprehenſions of their Schiſms and Diviſions. In the Churches of <hi>Aſia</hi> there were ſeveral things they were blamed for, as well as ſome things commended in them: But no hints of Separation from thoſe Churches, for thoſe evils found in them. So that the Scriptures give no countenance to total withdrawing from ſuch Churches, where many corruptions are, whilſt the eſſentials of Religion are preſerved.</p>
               <p>Some Scriptures i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>deed are very imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinently alledged for this practice (which may be cleared from the undeceiving of the weak in a few words) ſuch as 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6 14, 15, 16, 17. Which ſpeaks of ſeparation from Infidels and Idolaters in their Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latries, and ungodly fellowſhips, not of withdrawing from Chriſtian Aſſemblies, in the true Worſhip of God. So alſo 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.11. and 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 3.6, 14. Which Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures ſhew it a duty to withdraw from private perſons living in notorious, ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous ſins, for ſhaming the offendors, and preſerving the Churches; but ſpeak not a word of withdrawing from the true Worſhip of God in the publick Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:101381:40"/>of the Church, becauſe of controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal practiſes (yea, for ſome real evils there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in) for this will tend to the deſtruction of the Church<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which is contrary to the end of all Church-cenſures being for Edificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, not for deſtruction, 2 <hi>Cor</hi> 10.8.</p>
               <p>As for that Scripture, <hi>Revel</hi> 18.3. <hi>Come out of</hi> Babylon <hi>&amp;c.</hi> It may warrant a with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawing from the Idolatrous Worſhip of <hi>Rome,</hi> and the Abominations of Popery; from which (we before ſhewed) it's the duty of every good Chriſtian, that loves his Salvation, to depart: but it's groſly abuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed when it's made to plead for Separation from any of the reformed Churches, where (through the mercy of God) the Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentals of Faith, and eſſentials of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip are maintained; ſo that we ſee the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures will not warrant ſuch Separation.</p>
               <p n="2">(2.) Or if you will Reverence the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral ſuffrage of the Chriſtian Church, and of the moſt eminent Saints and Martyrs li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving therein, ever ſince Chriſts time to us (which ſurely however ſome ſlight, yet there's no ſmal weight in it, elſe the Apoſtle would not plead, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.16. We have no ſuch cuſtom nor the Churches of Chriſt) The moſt eminent Servants of Chriſt in in all Ages have conſtantly held and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed Communion with thoſe Churches
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:101381:40"/>where they lived, although very often, there were far greater corruptions therein, then can be found this day amongſt us, (as thoſe that are acquainted with Antiquity know well) and have ever blamed thoſe that have left the Churches Communion for ſuch cauſes as were above named; wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs the Cenſures paſt againſt the <hi>Novati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, Donatiſts, Audaeans,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>As for our Separation from <hi>Rome,</hi> our Proteſtant Divines plead the Fundamental errr found therein, and groſs Idolatries (which they muſt neceſſarily communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate in, if they withdraw not) perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and not leſſer matters. Did not thoſe hinder? they profeſs a readineſſe to communicate with her; and that they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from her no further, then ſhe departs from Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="3">(3.) Will you regard the judgment of the moſt eminent Divines (of almoſt all perſwaſions amongſt Proteſtants) that have lived in this and the former Age, [ſpeaking expreſly concerning Communion with the Church of <hi>England.</hi>] Then know, 1. That all forraign Divines of other Reformed Churches have approved of Communion with her, and been ready on all occaſions to give their fulleſt Teſtimony of their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like of rigid Separation from her. 2. All
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:101381:41"/>former Non-Conformiſts (who did diſſent in ſome ſmaller matters of Ceremonies, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> deſiring a forbearance as to their pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice in thoſe things, yet) have fully decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red againſt Separation from the Church of <hi>England,</hi> witneſs the writings of very many of them (worthy a ſerious peruſal at this day,) <hi>viz. Cartwright, Hilderſham, Bradſhaw Bayne Ball,</hi> many Others, and witneſs their practice formerly, and at this day. 3. <hi>Independents,</hi> See <hi>Apol Narrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the five diſſenting Brethren.</hi> page 5.6. Who fully teſtify againſt the practice 

<q>of the <hi>Browniſts,</hi> or rigid Separatiſts, whoſe fatal miſcarriages and Shipwrack, they call Landmarks to forewarn of thoſe Rocks and Shelves they ran upon. And declare their ſincere profeſſion to God and the World that all that conſciouſneſs of the defilements they conceived to cleave to the true Worſhip of God in the Congregations of <hi>England,</hi> or of the unwarranted power in Church-gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours exerciſed therein, did never work in them any other <hi>thought,</hi> much leſs o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, but that <hi>Multitudes</hi> of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rochial Congregations were the true Churches of Chriſt, and the Miniſtry thereof a true Miniſtry, much leſs did it ever <hi>enter into their hearts,</hi> to judge
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:101381:41"/>them Anti-Chriſtian, for ſo (they ſay) they could not but ſee they ſhould alſo condemn the Churches of <hi>Scotland, Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> &amp;c. as no Churches, which to ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine was an <hi>horrour</hi> to their thoughts, Yea, that they always profeſſed, and in thoſe times when the Churches of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> were the moſt, either actually over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpread with defilements, or in the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt danger thereof, and when them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves had no hopes of ever viſiting this Land in peace; that they would hold a Communion with them as the Churches of Chriſt. And yet they add further. Beſides this profeſſion, as a real Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, ſome of them, after they were actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in the Congregational way did Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize their Children in the Pariſhional Congregations; and occaſionally admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Lords Supper in their Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, ſome viſiting them in their <hi>Exile,</hi> upon that relation fellowſhip and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memberſhip they held in the Pariſh Churches in <hi>England.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>It may be ſome will ſay, they have more light now, then thoſe eminent Divines had in former times: But they bewray herein too great ignorance and arrogance; this point having been far more diſſenſed in former, then in theſe preſent times; in
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:101381:42"/>which the prejudice of moſt is ſuch, they have ſcarce conſidered what hath been ſaid againſt their opinions.</p>
               <p n="4">(4.) If you withdraw totally upon this Account, you ſhould then ſeparate from all the Churches, that now are or ever have been in the World; for what Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches are ſo pure but they have ſome de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, errors or corruptions? For the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Church, even 1260 years agone and upwards, there were as great corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in it, as any you can finde here, and greater alſo. For the Churches of your own perſwaſion, do you think them alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether perfect? Wiſe and underſtanding men are able to finde ſome things amiſs; yea ſome of your ſelves have acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed all things are not according to their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire: ſo as if you will bear with nothing but reject all parts of Communion, becauſe you cannot cloſe in ſome things, you muſt ſeparate from them too, and ſo turn Seek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, or become Hermites or Anchorites, and live alone; and at length ſeparate from your ſelves alſo, becauſe ſome things will appear blame-worthy in you alſo; whither will this lead you?</p>
               <p n="5">(5.) Have you no more love to, and care of the publick ſolemn Worſhip of God, then to caſt off all publick Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:101381:42"/>becauſe you diſlike ſome things in the Churches, where they are adminiſtred? It's the greateſt glory God hath in all the World to be ſolemnly Worſhipped in the publick aſſemblies: But if all ſhould withdraw from them for ſuch offence, what publick worſhip ſhould God have in this Nation? ſeeing other perſwaſions are not permitted to meet; nay, where would it be found in the whole World? ſeeing there's no Church on Earth, but hath ſome corruptions.</p>
               <p n="6">(6.) Let it be conſidered how unchri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian it is, to depart from the ſolemn Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances of Gods worſhip in thoſe Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches where the preſence of Chriſt is yet continued in them; have you any warrant to leave them, before Chriſt leave them? when God was greatly provoked by the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Church, ſo as he was about to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move from his Sanctuary, and ſtood at the Threſhold ready to leave them, we finde many godly ones mourning for the abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations of the times, but none haſtening to depart from that Church before the Lord departed. Now can you deny the preſence of the Lord in the Aſſemblies of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> wherein (as before was ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) the eſſentials of Faith and Worſhip be preſerved? if God ſhould be as unmerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:101381:43"/>as man is uncharitable, then wo to all the Churches of Chriſt throgh the World, nay, wo to your ſelves. But I queſtion not but there are thouſands can ſea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of Chriſt in the Congregations of <hi>England</hi> at this day, as well as in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer times, wherein the ſame Corruptions (at which ſo much offence is taken now) were urged to plead for a ſeparation then. Let ſuch as cry out ſo much of Popery in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, beware of that miſerable Popiſh er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, they reſtrain the Church and the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges thereof (the preſence of Chriſt and Salvation, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) to their own Sect and Party; and in the mean time caſting off the far greater part of the Catholick Church that maintain all the Eſſentials of Faith and Worſhip.</p>
               <p n="7">(7.) I might enumerate the many great miſchiefs that follow upon ſuch unwarran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Separation. It plainly tends to the diſhonor of Chriſt, and the reproach of the Chriſtian Religion; ſo the hinderance of the ſucceſs of the Goſpel and the Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Souls; ſo overthrow the Worſhip of God, and to open a Gap to <hi>Atheiſm</hi> and prophaneſs, to <hi>Hereſie</hi> and <hi>Popery,</hi> &amp;c, yea, to the utter ruine of the Chriſtian Church, <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.25.</p>
               <p>But it may ſeem needleſs to ſpend more
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:101381:43"/>words in ſo clear a caſe: nor ſhould I have ſaid thus much, had not I been com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled thereto by the uncatholick (nay, I confidently call it unchriſtian) practice of many well meaning people, through their too great prejudice in other Temptations, who do totally withdraw themſelves from the publick Congregations in <hi>England</hi> and the true Worſhip of God therein.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Having given my advice to hold Communion with the Churches of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> in the True Worſhip of God, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the corruptions ſuppoſed to be therein. I do next adviſe, on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hand, not to communicate with her (nor with any Church in the World) in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny evil, but if any thing profeſſed or practiſed therein, be found really ſinfull (which may be ſuppoſed of any Church upon Earth) in that thing to withdraw and have no fellowſhip in it, to keep your ſelves pure from the ſame; yea, I ſhal add further, if there be any thing that ſhall but appear ſinful to thee, (thy Conſcience, after humble and diligent ſearching of the Word, telling thee, this is ſin) then to ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend thy conſent or practice, in that par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, till it appear otherwiſe to thee. I would be here ſo far from urging any to do that act, that a truly tender Conſcience
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:101381:44"/>upon probable grounds may ſcruple as ſinful; that I would rather perſwade ſuch to ſuſpend their acting therein, till they be better convinced of the lawfulneſſe of it;
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Sanderſ. de Juram</hi> p. 84. The dictate of Conſcience whether right or erroneous, ever bindeth not to act againſt it.</note> and (ſuppoſing it be a thing not in its own nature neceſſary, but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong things diſputable and tolerable) I would rather become an hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Suitor to Authority (could my inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion any whit avail herein) for Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence in ſuch a caſe; then to be a violent inforcer of any, by Terrours or Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Law, to go againſt their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences to pleaſe men.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Yet becauſe Conſcience may be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luded, and my call that ſinfull, which is lawful, and a duty; and ſo induce men to withdraw in ſuch Acts of Communion, as neither the Law of God, nor men will allow them to withdraw from: for poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly the Devil may get into the Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of men, and delude them; And the Conſcience may tell one, he muſt ſeparate from Baptiſm, becauſe Infant-Baptiſm is Anti-Chriſtian; Another he muſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw from the Lords Supper, becauſe of mixt Communion therein; A third from the hearing of the Word, becauſe the call
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:101381:44"/>of Miniſters is Anti-Chriſtian; A fourth, he muſt caſt off Sabbaths, yea Scriptures and all Goſpel Ordinances, becauſe aboliſhed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> (All this we have too ſad experience of in our times) Let therefore every good C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian labour for a due information of his Conſcience in ſuch points as he Scruples Communion in, and not think his bare plea of Conſcience wil warrant his total neglect of any duty. Though his ſuſpending his own actings (till he may ſatisfie Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence about them) may be granted: yet poſſibly a total neglect in ſome things, will not be granted <hi>Impune,</hi> by the Law of God or man.</p>
               <p>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">An erring Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence cannot diſcharge any from a duty, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not a Law-ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, but ſubject to the Law. <hi>Pariſiens.</hi>
                  </note> Now here it may be expected I ſhould offer my help toward the ſatisfying Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in ſuch Scruples, as commonly do occurr (this day) to thoſe that withdraw in whole or in part from the Communion of the Church of <hi>England</hi> in its preſent State and Adminiſtrations. But to do this fully, would too much diſproportion this part of my diſcourſe, to the other parts aforego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; I rather chuſe to ſend them to thoſe Treatiſes of ſuch eminent Non-Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts, as have written fully on this ſubject-eſpecially
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:101381:45"/>to Mr. <hi>W<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Bradſhaw's</hi> Book of the unreaſonableneſs of ſeparation prefaced to, &amp; publiſhed by Dr. <hi>Ames;</hi> and to Mr. <hi>Jo. Ball</hi> his tryal of the grounds tending to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration,
* only recommending a few ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Rules, which being obſerved, may be uſeful in order thereunto, and ſo conclude my Diſcourſe,</p>
               <div type="note">
                  <p>* The Reader is Advertiſed, that there is Publiſhed in Print, an Aſwer to that part of Mr. <hi>Ball's</hi> Book, which is a Diſcourſe of the lawfulneſs of a ſtinted Liturgy and ſet forms of Prayer, under the name of Mr. <hi>Jo. Cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton.</hi> The Anſwer is highly valued by ſome, but by comparing the Diſcourſe and the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer together, it may be ſeen, that great injury is done to Mr. <hi>Ball</hi> and to Mr. <hi>Cotton</hi> both, and alſo that the Reader is groſly abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by it; for it is not that Diſcourſe Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at <hi>Cambridge, 1640.</hi> which is therein anſwered; (but probably ſome imperfect Notes, before that was publiſhed) which is evident, not only becauſe the number and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the Arguments anſwered do differ from thoſe laid down in that Diſcourſe; But eſpecially becauſe the principal things given in anſwer by Mr. <hi>Cotton,</hi> are ſo fully ſpoken to by Mr. <hi>Ball</hi> herein, (by way of reply to <hi>Johnſon, Greenwood</hi> and others, that for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly objected the ſame things;) that there ſeems nothing more requiſite to be ſaid by way of reply thereunto. Thus much was needfull to be certifyed, becauſe ſome have ſlighted Mr. <hi>Balls</hi> Book, not deeming it worth reading; becauſe ſufficiently anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by Mr. <hi>Cotton,</hi> whereas indeed this Book may ſerve for a ſufficient reply to his Anſwer.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:101381:45"/>
               <head>CHAP. IX.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Wherein are laid down ſome general Rules of Caution to preſerve Chriſtians from raſh and unjuſt ſeparation. The Concluſion of the Diſcourſe.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>ALthough the anſwering all objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and ſatisfying every ſcruple that may occurr about this point of Communion with the Congregations in <hi>England,</hi> is a work too large to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaken in theſe Papers; and indeed need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs in reſpect of that abundant pains ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken therein by thoſe Writers before refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to; yet becauſe I may not leave the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber and humble Chriſtian, altogether with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out help, that is deſirous to find ſomething
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:101381:46"/>here, that may ſatisfy his Conſcience about the premiſes; I ſhal lay down ſome gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Rules of caution, which being duly conſidered and improved, may through the bleſſing of the Lord much conduce to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent or heal raſh and unjuſt ſeparation, which are theſe that follow.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Do not raſhly ſeparate for ſuch things as have been found in almoſt all the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of Chriſt upon Earth, both in former and latter times: the reaſon is, becauſe (though we ſay not, the Church is ſo abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely Infallible, that it cannot err in the leaſt particular; yet we may eaſily defend That) the Univerſal Church in all places and ages cannot err ſo dangerouſly, ſo as good Chriſtians ought not to keep com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with her, but are bound to make ſeparation from her; for this would in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr that ſhe hath wholly fallen from Chriſt and her bond of Union with him is diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and he is no longer preſent with her (for till then Chriſtians are not wholly to ſeparate from her) yea, that Chriſt hath no Church in the World, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And if ſo, what will become of the promiſes of Chriſt, that <hi>Hel gates ſhal not prevail againſt her,</hi> that <hi>he will be with her to the end of the World;</hi> that <hi>he will ſend his Spirit to lead her into all Truth,</hi> and <hi>it ſhall abide with her for ever;</hi>
                  <pb n="82" facs="tcp:101381:46"/>which promiſes though directly and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marily they were made to the Apoſtles, who had the ſpecial preſence of Chriſt and the guidance of his holy Spirit in the moſt eminent manner, yet were made to them for the behoofe of the Church Univerſal, and ſhal be verified to it.</p>
               <p>This duly conſidered, would much pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent the ſcandal taken at Biſhops, at forms of Prayer, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For who is there (if ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the State of the Church) that knows not that Biſhops (even in a ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periority of power and jurisdiction over other Miniſters) have been in the Church of Chriſt almoſt univerſally from the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles times to our dayes; and that ſet Forms of Prayers, have been of exceeding long continuance in the Chriſtian Curches, through the World. Therefore ſuch as ſeparate for theſe things now, muſt have been led by the ſame principle to have ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated from almoſt all the Churches of Chriſt upon Earth; which thing how dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous it is, needs not much to be ſpoken to her, to manifeſt the ſame.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Let not inconveniences, defects, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, or errors Circumſtantial, cauſe you to withdraw Communion wholly from the Churches of Chriſt in the ſubſtantial duties of Gods Worſhip, where the eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tials
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:101381:47"/>are preſerved; though ſome leſſer e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils may be found, do not utterly refuſe Communion there. The Lord Jeſus wil not reject ſuch Churches, therefore do not you.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ames. eaſ.</hi> Lib 4. Cap 24.</note> This hath paſſed for good Divinity generally amongſt Non-Conformiſts who ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge Communion may be maintained, where ſome divine inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are wanting, and ſome humane ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditaments meerly extrinſical are joyned to Divine Worſhip.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Commiſ. papers.</hi> p. 3.12.</note> They ſay that where the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantials of Worſhip are preſerved,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Bayne</hi> on <hi>Eph</hi> 2.15</note> though the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal forms and modes be more inconvenient, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orderly and defective;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hilderſ.</hi> on <hi>Pſ.</hi> 51. <hi>Lect.</hi> 35.</note> yet its lawfull, yea a duty to offer ſuch Worſhip to God rather then none at all. That what e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver is not in our power to reform, it ſhall be our zeal and piety to tolerate, and with patience to bear, &amp; in ſuch Churches there may be more cauſe to rejoyce then to grieve. Indeed the contrary practice would lead to ſeparation from all the Churches of Chriſt upon Earth, for which of them all is perfect?</p>
               <p n="3">3. As Chriſtians ſhould fly from what
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:101381:47"/>is really Idolatry, Will-worſhip, Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtianiſm, Popery, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> So let them not be affrighted with thoſe names, when im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed on things, without good grounds, leſt they be ſcared from neceſſary duty and Worſhip; for theſe terrifying names have been abuſively applyed to deterr weak people from the true Worſhip of God. <hi>E. G.</hi> Idolatry, Will-worſhip, ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gery, hath been charged upon ſet forms of Prayer, and they have been cenſured to be forbidden in the ſecond Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. But what Chriſtian (not prepoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed beforehand with prejudice againſt them) can finde them therein condemned, or in any of the Commentaries of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets or Apoſtles, or in any Expoſition of antient or modern Writers till ſome few of latter times? May not any ſimple plain hearted Chriſtian (to whoſe apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons the Scriptures are ſuted, in all neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary duties, <hi>Pſal</hi> 19.7.) profeſs, he is not able to ſee any ſuch thing, but on the contrary he findeth ſet forms, not onely uſed and preſcribed in the Old Teſtament, but alſo in the New; he finds Jeſus Chriſt giving a form to his Diſciples, as <hi>John</hi> did to his; and how can he then reſent thoſe charges of Imagery, Idolatry, Superſtition, but as meer Scare-crows? The like may be
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:101381:48"/>ſaid of the charge of Popery, drawn up by ſome againſt the preſent forms of Prayer by Law eſtabliſhed; that they are taken out of the Maſs Book, are Popiſh Prayers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which affrights ſome poor weak Chriſtians, they are afraid to come near them. When as it cannot be denyed, that (1.) they were compiled by ſundry godly men of the Reformed Religion, ſome of them afterwards Martyrs in Queen <hi>Marys</hi> dayes, &amp; were ever highly valued by them. (2.) The Papiſts have ever had them in deteſtation. Queen <hi>Mary</hi> is reported to have razed them out of the Parliament Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords, ſo as it could not (till ſome hath late Acts paſſed) be well known which was the authorized Book; and <hi>Harding</hi> their great Champion ſaith of it, in his diſpute with Biſhop <hi>Jewel</hi> on <hi>Art.</hi> 3. That it's ſuch a ſervice as their good Catholicks cannot joyn with us in; not only becauſe it is in the vulgar Tongue: but becauſe (ſaith he) many neceſſary things are wanting in it, and many things repugnant to the Faith and cuſtome of the Catholick Church. (3.) Popery cannot return upon us, whilſt the ſaid Common-Prayer-Book is kept unal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered, how can their proper Sacrifice, Communion in one kind, Prayers to Saints <hi>&amp;c.</hi> come in, whilſt this is kept up and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved; and as for the taking theſe Prayers
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:101381:48"/>out of the Maſs Book, the truth is this; there are ſeveral Prayers of Antient Fathers (uſed before Popery was in the World) which the Papiſts corrupting and abuſing in their Maſs, our firſt Reformers purged out what corruptions the Papiſts had brought in, and did retain thoſe antient Prayers according to their Primitive Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution. All this will be readily acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged by them, that judging this book unneceſſary and inconvenient, do deſire a Reformation therein; and is there any thing in all this that ſhall ſo affright good Chriſtians out of the Church? Concerning the charge of Antichriſtianiſm, it is ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon a word in the mouths of all that liſt to rayle, that its no ſcandal to any, till the thing be fully proved; if Biſhops, and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> be judged by any to be Anti-Chriſtian, I ſhal ſend them to that moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent piece of Dr. <hi>Moore,</hi> his <hi>Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of Iniquity,</hi> where they may ſee the Idea of <hi>Anti-Chriſtianiſm</hi> opened, and thence be informed, whom this cenſure beſt befits</p>
               <p n="4">IV. Take heed of pretending to greater purity and ſtrictneſs about Church Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion and Adminiſtrations, then the Word of God commends, or the examples of Chriſt and the Apoſtles and the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Church do commend; nor be
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:101381:49"/>ſo extremely rigid as not to bear with things that they have Tolerated. It is an obſervable rule laid down by wiſe and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent Divines, that too much ſtrictneſſe and ſeverity often doth injury the Church more then profite it; its the way to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn Churches not to reform them, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially this ſeverity is unbecoming private Chriſtians, who having no Authority, yet complain, ſuch perſons, and ſuch things are defilements, they muſt ſeparate from them, they muſt not touch the unclean thing: ſuch ſhould take heed that they be not righteous over much, and not dare to be wiſe above what is written, leſt their too much affected purity and miſguided zeal hurt more the Church of Chriſt, and their own Souls then the corruptions they ſo much complain of. <hi>Calvin adv. Anab.</hi> Art. 2. <hi>Cum ſub ſpecie ſtudii perfectionis im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfectionem nulam tollerare poſſumus; tune Diabolum nos tumefacere ſuperbia, et hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi ſeducere moneamur.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">V. Have publick Spirits, and look not ſo much on ſuch things as are moſt deſira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in your eyes, and conduce to your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt: as on what tends to the furtherance of the Goſpel, and the good of the Church in generall. There have been very few in our unhappie dayes, but have been ſo ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerly
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:101381:49"/>contending for their private opinions and wayes, that the publick intereſt of the Chriſtian Religion, and of the Churches peace and welfare hath been almoſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten by them, from whence have come in ſuch an inundation of Errours, Hereſies, Profaneneſſe and Atheiſm, that the Church hath been almoſt ruined thereby. In vain do we contend about the greater purity and perfection of the Chriſtian Religion, when the verie being and life of it by our contentions and diviſions is indangered, what will become of our conteſts for grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter reformation in Diſcipline, Worſhip, &amp;c. If the Chriſtian Religion it ſelf be loſt? They are the beſt and wiſeſt Chriſtians that have moſt indeavoured, that the main Fundamental Doctrines and duties of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion may be preſerved, though in the mean time they yield in ſmall matters that concern the beautie and perfection thereof, waiting in a wiſe and peaceable manner til the Lord will grant them their deſires there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in alſo, in his own way and time.</p>
               <p n="6">VI. Take heed of running into manifeſt ſin and evil upon fears of what is only ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to be ſo. <hi>viz.</hi> Of caſting off Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, neglecting of the publick Worſhip of God, breach of the peace of the <hi>Church, &amp;c.</hi> Upon pretence of ſuppoſed evils in
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:101381:50"/>Communion. The commands of God for his Worſhip and Ordinances &amp; the Church peace, are clear and cogent; the matters ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted againſt, are dark and diſputable points of controverſie, and the far greater part of the Churches of Chriſt on earth have approved of them; therefore be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid while you would ſhun an evil ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, you run not into another that is a real and far greater evil. A truly tender conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence ſhould fear evil on either hand, and on this ſide rather then that.</p>
               <p n="7">VII. Charge not on your ſelves o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mens ſins, but look to your own wayes and duties. If you judge Superiors to ſin in their impoſitions, or Biſhops in any Command, or Miniſters in their Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity; if you find ſin in laxneſſe of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline, in looſe admiſſions to the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances &amp;c. It's not your ſin who ſtill Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate in the Ordinances of Chriſt, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided you do your parts and Office. It were ſad living in any Church in the World, if the ſins of others ſhould be char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged on ſuch as have neither calling not power to reform them; fitter it is by far to mourn and pray for Redreſſing of ſuch evils, then to run out of the Church for them.</p>
               <p n="8">VIII. Take heed of that great and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:101381:50"/>miſtake, that nothing is to be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in and about the government and admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of the Church of Chriſt, in the leaſt Circumſtantials thereof, but what is particularly and clearly held forth in the Scriptures. This miſtake hath occaſioned many needleſs ſcruples in the minds of weak Chriſtians, and much promoted groundleſſe ſeparation. It is a Rule laid down by a whole Aſſemblie of Divines,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aſſem. Conf.</hi> of Faith. c 1.</note> many of them not much affected to the preſent eſtabliſhment, [That there are ſome cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances concerning the Worſhip of God and Government of the Church, common to humane actions and Societies which are to be ordered by the light of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and Chriſtian prudence according to the general Rules of the Word] And the ſame is practiſed among all thoſe that are moſt averſe to the communion of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> who retain amongſt themſelves many things, that they can pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce little true-Scripture-proofs for, but only practiſe them prudentially as beſt conducing to the welfare of their Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, and (as they judge) to the Order of Gods Worſhip therein, and ſome have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geniouſly acknowledged as much. If you ſearch the Scriptures impartiallie concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:101381:51"/>Church-government you will finde therein little beſides, the main Eſſentials of it, as that the Church is to be Governed; and that by its proper Officers, and dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions how they ſhould be qualified and ſet apart for their Office, what the ſeverall duties belonging to their Office are, and ſome general directions about the manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thereof; All which may ſute with the ſeveral forms of Government that have been competitors amongſt us wherein the power of Chriſts Offi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cers is further extended or more reſtrained,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Stillingf iren.</hi> pt 2. c <hi>4.</hi> &amp;c <hi>8.</hi>
                  </note> wherein ſome act in a ſuperior, others in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a coordinate way) and therefore very many learned and godly men have judged, that no one form of government was preſcribed as neceſſary in the Church; but it's left to be ſuted to the condition of thoſe King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms and Nations where the Church ſhall be planted. The like may be ſaid concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Goſpel Worſhip; The main duties and Ordinances of it are preſcribed, and thoſe things wherein the Eſſence of them ſtands, are more fully and clearly expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; but their circumſtances and manner of performance are only couched under ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Rules. This may be ſhewed abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly by inſtances in the ſeveral parts of Worſhip as Prayer, Preaching, Sacraments,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:101381:51"/>&amp;c, but it is done by others ſully and muſt be omitted here, becauſe of the brevity of theſe Rules.</p>
               <p>Nor doth this derogate from the ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency of the Scriptures, nor argue want of wiſdome and faithfulneſſe in Chriſt (as ſome plead) if he ſhould not preſcribe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Particular, as <hi>Moſes</hi> did even to the Pinns of the Tabernacle; for the Scriptures are ſufficient for that end God gave them, to make wiſe to Salvation, and in order thereunto to inſtruct us in all neceſſarie points of Faith and Practice: and for Church-government and Worſhip, there's enough in theſe Eſſentials laid down in Scripture for the preſerving the welfare of the Church in the World, and ſecuring of the true and pure Worſhip of God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong men (thoſe being duly obſerved) And wherein then are the Scriptures to be argued of inſufficiencie, if they leave ſome particular circumſtances undetermined? And for the charge of unfaithfulneſſe in Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, if he ſhould not particularize thoſe things, it's ſtrangely preſumptuous. Such ſhould rather ſhew where Chriſt hath particularly determined all thoſe circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, then impute unfaithfulneſſe unto him, if he do not what they wold have to be done. There is not the like Reaſon to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:101381:52"/>all circumſtances in the Chriſtian Churches, as was in the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Church, the one being in its Minority, the other grown up to a ſtate of greater libertie and perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 10. A Boy that goeth to School hath his Leſſon ſet him, and in every particular he is ſtinted to his work; but when he goes to the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſitie, he only hears Lectures, hath ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Rules for his ſtudy, and is left to his own diſpoſition, for order and manner of his ſtudies. Beſides the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Church was confined to one Nation, that had its ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil government and Laws from God as wel as its Church inſtiutions: but the Chriſtian Church, being to ſpread throughout the World under different civil governments, different circumſtances, might beſt ſute with the ſtate and condition of different People.</p>
               <p n="9">IX. Take heed of Reſiſting the ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of God, whilſt you profeſs to oppoſe the inſtitutions of Men. My meaning is, whilſt you withſtand humane inventions (as you ſuppoſe them) in the Worſhip of God, beware you oppoſe not lawfull Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority (which is the Ordinance of God) in what they injoin in and about the Worſhip of God according to the power given them of the Lord. That Magiſtrates have the
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:101381:52"/>care of the Churches in their Dominions, committed to them, &amp; ſhould ſee to the due adminiſtration of the Worſhip and Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of God therein (as well as to the outward peace and proſperitie of the civil State) may be manifeſt to all that are willing to ſee it, by the laudable examples of godly Kings in former times, ſuch as <hi>David, Solomon, Aſa, Jehoſaphat, Heze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiah, &amp;c.</hi> Whoſe chiefeſt care was about Religion, and the Worſhip of God in their Dominions. Indeed they are not to make any new inſtitutions of Worſhip nor alter any thing that is particularlie injoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Word of God; But they are to ſee that all things be adminiſtred according to the ſame. And in the particular circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances undetermined by God, they have a power to order and ſettle things accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the generall Rules laid down in the Word; and (however you plead, you are not to be the Servants of Men) you muſt be therein ſubject to them in the Lord.</p>
               <p>It hath been a Notion taken up by ſome, That as in former times, the Saints have ſuffered in giving Teſtimony to the prieſtly Office of Jeſus Chriſt; ſo they muſt bear witneſs to his Kingly Office, what ever they ſuffer, and not yield to any Commandments of men in and about the
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:101381:53"/>Worſhip of God; But let ſuch take heed that they oppoſe not his Kingly Office, when they ſeem to ſtand up for it. For if Magiſtrates and Rulers be his Vice-gerents (as certainly they are) and there is a care of his Worſhip delegated unto them, and ſome power for ordering affairs in his Church in matters of outward conveniency and order, where he hath not expreſly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined, in withſtanding them in ſuch things, they may reſiſt Jeſus Chriſt himſelf. Indeed it may be a further Scruple in caſe Magiſtrates injoyning things inexpedient and inconvenient, and ſo ſwerve from thoſe general Rules, that they are to go by, whether they are to yeeld to them in ſuch things or no? But if the judgement of Non-Conformiſts may be taken herein,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Baxt. five Diſp.</hi> p. <hi>460, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> they determine in ſuch caſes it's better to obey then to withſtand, they may ſin in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding ſuch things, and yet ſubjects not ſin in obeying them when commanded; they are Judges in ſuch particular caſes to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine what is expedient, as the Word of God determines what is neceſſary; and herein they follow the judgment of <hi>Calvin, Ep.</hi> 379, which have been ever approved by them, who ſpeaking of things of this Nature, Saith, ſome things neither right
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:101381:53"/>nor profitable, but ſcandalous and drawing evil Conſequences with them; yet not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing repugnant to the word (in any expreſs determination of it) muſt be borne of the godly Brethren, when they cannot help it, and the Churches of Chriſt not forſaken. And indeed if this ſhould not be admitted, but ſo often as any ſhall judge ſuch or ſuch matters inexpedient, they might withſtand: the Axe ſeems to be laid at the roots of all government, and there wold be little order in the Churches of Chriſt. There is no ſociety in the World but a yielding in ſome things is neceſſary, for the peace and welfare of that Society.</p>
               <p n="10">X. Let not any principles or practices that you have inconſideratly taken up, ſo far ingage you, as to make you loath to teturn to wayes of Truth and ſoberneſs. Some have (it may be unwillingly and with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luctancy only, through the violence of ſome of their own party) been led into the wayes of rigid ſeparation, to condemn all other Churches, but their own (howe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſound in all the main Fundamental and neceſſary Doctrines and duties of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity) and to refuſe any Communion with them (though this hath been condemned by the moſt wiſe and knowing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o their own profeſſion,
<note place="margin">. <hi>T. G. Mr. Cotton</hi>
                  </note> ſtiled
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:101381:54"/>by ſome the bitter root of ſeparation, the way God nere bleſt with peace and holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) And now to return to wayes of ſobriety, and own ſuch as they have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly ſo hotly contended againſt, they know not how to do it. There is natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally in man a tenaciouſneſſe of thoſe wayes and opinions they have once profeſſed, that they are loath to recede from them, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally if they have contended for them, this is a great piece of denyal. Men would ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther yeeld in their patrimony (ſaith <hi>Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer</hi>) then in their opinion. Beſides, they may undergo the heavy charge of Apoſtacy,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ep.</hi> to <hi>Jo<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> a Laſco</hi>
                  </note> and deſerting the Truth, and changing their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and this deterrs many from wayes of truth and Sobriety. But it would be conſidered, it's no diſcharge for the wiſeſt, holyeſt, and moſt learned Men to retract in ſome controverſal opinions or practices; <hi>Auguſtine</hi> who was eſteemed the moſt learned of the Fathers, Writes ſeveral Books of Retractations; and <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome</hi> to <hi>Ruffinus,</hi> ſaith, never bluſh Man to change thy opinion, for neither you nor I, nor any Perſon living are of ſo great Authority, as to be aſhamed to confeſs that they have Erred. And as for the charge of <hi>Apoſtacy</hi> and changing your Religion in
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:101381:54"/>ſuch a caſe as this is, it's a great miſtake to affirm this; for if you ſearch the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, Apoſtacy is a falling away from the main Fundamental confeſſed Doctrines of the Goſpel and duties of godlyneſs, into manifeſt hereſie or wickedneſſe, not the changing a mans judgment or practice in ſome points diſputable amongſt the godly and Orthodox, ſaith Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> in his <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity.</hi> Be it known to all the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts in the World, that our Religion is not changed at all, our Worſhip is the ſame, whether within Book or without: our Prayers are the ſame for matter with thoſe in the Common Prayer Book; and if I ſhold one day uſe the Common Prayer Book, and another day forbear it, I ſhould not change the Worſhip of God, to pray is part of his Worſhip but whether it be in a Book or out of it, is no part at all, but a mode or circumſtance which may be altered as oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion ſerveth. Elſewhere the ſame lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and pious perſon ſheweth what yielding in things lawful the Scripture recommendeth to us, from the example of St. <hi>Paul,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Five <hi>Diſp.</hi> p. 488.</note> when he circumciſed Timothy, <hi>Act</hi> 16.3. And when he took the men and purified him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with them in the Temple, to ſignifie the accompliſhment of the dayes of Purifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, <hi>&amp;c. Act.</hi> 21.26, 27. So alſo from
<pb n="001" facs="tcp:101381:55"/>what he ſaith, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.19, 20. I am made all things to all men, that I might by all means ſave ſome, and this I do for the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpels ſake.</p>
               <p n="11">XI. I add but one Rule of Caution more againſt a very common but dangerous mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake, which is an occaſion to many of running in to Error and Hereſie, as well as into Schiſm and Separation, <hi>viz.</hi> Take heed of ſetting up your own apprehenſions, and conceits of the ſenſe of Scriptures a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout controverted points, as infallible O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles, that you truſt ſo confidently to, that you will indanger the Churches peace and your own ſafety for the maintaining of them, where you have not all thoſe neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary helps and means that are requiſite to the finding out the minde of God therein. Some that have their minds fore-ſtalled with an opinion or perſwaſion, getting a Bible into their hands, preſently conceive what ever they meet withall to make for their opinion<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and begin to be more confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent then an hundred wiſer and more diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning perſons dare to be, who know their own darkneſs and ignorance, and the myſteriouſneſs of the things controverted, though they have far greater evidence of Scripture, and reaſon for them. This car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries men into ſuch wilde fancies &amp; ſtrange
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:101381:55"/>deluſions ſometimes, as bring them under the juſt cenſure of <hi>Fanaticiſm,</hi> (a name which is too unjuſtly applyed to others, more ſober and pious Chriſtians:) Though the Fundamental and neceſſary Doctrines, and duties of Chriſtianity, are ſo plainly laid down in Scripture, that the weakeſt Chriſtians may underſtand them; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore have much profit by holy and humble Meditation in the Word of God day and night: yet Points controverted are often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times hidden from ordinary underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, that know not the Languages and proper Idioms of Scripture and cuſtoms of the Church, and other advantages of learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; that its ordinarily impoſſible, they ſhould find out the minde of God therein. It's a vain deluſion to think, that the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit (that ſome pretend to, more confident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly then they have cauſe) ſhould diſcover all deep myſteries and obſcure points of controverſie to thoſe that have but ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry underſtandings, and are wholly deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of outward neceſſary means and hopes for the gaining knowledge thereby: the Spirit of God teaches not by ſuch immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate <hi>Enthuſiaſmes,</hi> but by irradiating the minde and elevating the reaſon that is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed in ſearching the Truth in all Gods appointed means; and doth alſo help the
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:101381:56"/>weak to underſtand ſavourily all thoſe plain and neceſſary Truths that tend to godlineſſe, and to conform their hearts and lives to the love and obedience of them. It were more becoming weak Chriſtians in matters diſputable to conſult with the Writings of able and learned Expoſitors that have al thoſe advantages which them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves want, and not to preſume too much on their own underſtandings in ſuch things which would be accounted unſufferable preſumption in other Arts and Sciences, and cannot be leſs in Divinity, wherein the greateſt myſteries are contained. Other Rules of Caution might here be laid down which (to avoid prolixity) I forbear to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerate, recommending the ſerious con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of these things to the ſober and humble Chriſtian, as greatly conducing to keep him from the by-paths of unjuſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration; and here conclude with my hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Prayer to God, even the Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that he would grant to the Profeſſors of Chriſtianity in all Nations (both Rulers and People) to minde more, and to be more zealous for the great and Fundamental points of Faith and Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip neceſſary to Salvation: and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend leſs about things not in their own na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture neceſſary; that high impoſitions might
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:101381:56"/>not occaſion violent oppoſitions: nor theſe again produce further impoſitions. But we may love one another unfainedly for the great things we are united in, &amp; bear with one another m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re in things wherein difference is tolerable, and all may ſeek the unity, peace, and welfare of the Church, and the good of one another, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Then ſhould Religion flouriſh the Goſpel be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced, the fame of God be honoured, the Souls of men edified, and all may walk in the fear of God, and comfort of the Holy Ghoſt: unto which let every good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian ſay, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
